<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ouranoskopia, or, The contemplation of the heavens, in a perpetual speculum, or general prognostication for ever wherein is succinctly demonstrated the names and natures of the signs, planets and aspects, terms of art, order of the spheres, the colours, magnitudes, motions, solid proportions and distances of the seven planets from the earth ... / by Iames Corss ...</title>
            <author>Corss, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12711348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12711348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1524:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ouranoskopia, or, The contemplation of the heavens, in a perpetual speculum, or general prognostication for ever wherein is succinctly demonstrated the names and natures of the signs, planets and aspects, terms of art, order of the spheres, the colours, magnitudes, motions, solid proportions and distances of the seven planets from the earth ... / by Iames Corss ...</title>
                  <author>Corss, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 81, [3] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by a society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>"To the truely noble, most worthy and singular patronage of vertue, my honoured friend, Thomas Wood, the author, in testimony of his (endeared) affection, and gratitude for civilities received, humbly presents his Uranoscopia [signed] Iames Corss" -- opposite t.p.</note>
                  <note>Running title: Uranoscopia.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped, stained and tightly bound with print-showthrough and some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or, The contemplation of the Heavens, in a perpetual Speculum, or general <hi>Prognoſtication</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſuccinctly demonſtrated the Names and Natures of the Signs, Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and Aſpects, Terms of Art, order of the Spheres, the Colours, Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Motions, Solid Proportions and Diſtances of the ſeven Planets from the earth. The natural Cauſes and Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the Eclipſes of the Lumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Earth-quakes, Thunders, Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and Comets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amplified with ſuch Precepts and Examples and Operations, that any of ordinary capacity (by their own enduſtry) may be enabled to reſolve moſt propoſitions in Aſtronomy, the right and oblique aſcenſions and deſcenſions of all the Planets and fixed Stars: To calculate the Diameters, Circumferences, Solidity and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies of all Globs and Spheres: The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicall Letters, Golden-numbers, Epacts, Moveable feaſts and ages of the Moon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for any time paſt, preſent, or to come.</p>
            <p>By <hi>IAMES CORSS</hi> Philomath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by a Society of <hi>Stationers,</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:2"/>
            <p>To the truely Noble, moſt Worthy and Singular Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of Vertue, my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friend, <hi>THOMAS WOOD</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author, in Teſtimony of his (endeared) affection, and gratitude for civilities received, humbly preſents his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RANOSCOPIA.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iames Corſs.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a crown atop a shield</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>To the as much ſingular for Vertue, as eminent for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Magnificent and Illuſtrious Lord, <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Glencairn,</hi> Lord <hi>Kilmars</hi> and <hi>Finlayſtoun, Cuninghame,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Illuſtrious Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have brought forth to breath the Common Air, this ſmall Tract, at the deſire and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of ſeveral (ingenious) Gentlemen, whoſe high merits, ſtraightly requires at my hands, a devoutly-obedient, ſtrict and ſudden performance, of their imperious and not to be queſtioned commands. If the Rayes of your Tranſcendant Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude had not given it life, I was without any hope (after I had conceived it) ever to ſee it breath. And now I am conſtrained to dedicate it unto your Lordſhip, before whom it ought to have appeared as richly endued with Ornaments, as you are with Vertues. Vouchſafe (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) to accept, in excuſe of my boldneſſe, the neceſſity of my obedience, by receiving this Infant into your high and gracious protection,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:4"/>
            <p>Being now delivered from the Preſſe, I am humbly bold to preſent it unto your Lordſhips Patronage, at no leſſe a diſtance then the Center can be ſuppoſed from the Circumference, not queſtioning but your high candour and courteſie will acquit me of the preſumption.</p>
            <p>Great Lord, I do it not, as if I hereby thought to add the leaſt Atome to your Tranſcendant Magnitude and Merit; (a thing impoſſible to your inferiours) but to ſet the better Luſtre upon my Labours, that their paſſage through the world may be the more current, as having the impreſſe of your High and Illuſtrious Name and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon them. Beſides your exquiſite ſkill in, and affection to all Mathematical Arts and Sciences, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to entitle you <hi>Mecoenas</hi> to a Piece of far greater worth and Learning then this I preſent you with: But the meridian of my glory is this, <hi>That the Pilot of my poor Veſſel is a Perſon moſt Illuſtrious and Excellent, in whoſe breaſt, the ſublimity of all vertues are concentred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope your Lordſhip will excuſe the meanneſſe of the preſent, (ſeeing the ſmalleſt Penny is ſtamped with His Majeſties Impreſſe, as well as the greateſt <hi>Jacobus</hi>) for Princes cannot expect from their Inferiours Preſents proportionable to their high magnitude and merit. And though I cannot now (by this affectionatly-bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt) avoid the cenſure of raſhneſſe, yet this is my comfort, that I have but aſſayed to do that whereunto I was wholly oblieged (by your High-meriting favours) and that with the greateſt affection and ſubmiſſion ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, that the world may know how much I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt devoted ſervant, <hi>JAMES CORSS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have oftentimes lamented with my ſelf to ſee ſo many Learned Mathematicians to ariſe in ſundry parts of the world, and ſo few to appear in our Native Country. In other things we are parallel with (I ſhall not ſay in a ſuperlative degree far above) other Nations; but in Arts and Sciences Mathematical, all exceed us. And had not that thrice Noble and Illuſtrious Lord, viz. <hi>John Lord Nepper, Barron of Marchiſton, &amp;c.</hi> preſerved the honour of our Nation by his admirable and more then mortal inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Logarithms,</hi> we ſhould have been buried in oblivion, in the memories of Forraign Nations; but his famous Works, and admirable Skill in ſublime Sciences, together with his unparalled Invention aforeſaid, makes us co-equal to the moſt ſubtile Nations in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. Certainly, the good Angels of God in an extraordinary Revelation made known to this Illiſtrious divine Lord, the <hi>grand Secret of Numbers perfection,</hi> which all the world had been ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for but in vain, untill this great Lord and Luminary, (the <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of all wiſe men) made the light thereof to ſhine not only in <hi>Britains</hi> Horizon, but over all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſs; who now are enabled by the divine beams of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred mind to ſee into the bottom of <hi>Numbers</hi> Myſtery, &amp;c. He was a mighty <hi>Moecenas</hi> to all <hi>Mathematicall</hi> Studies, but who will imitate him now, I know not. <hi>O Noble Lord</hi> Naper, <hi>Baron of</hi> Marchiſton, <hi>&amp;c. my Genius is too dull to commend thee, or to give thy ſacred wiſdom the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand part of thy due praiſe,</hi> &amp;c. But to return, the only thing that produceth ſo few <hi>Mathematicians</hi> in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and ancient Kingdom, is firſt, lack of encouragement; There's no man (of eminency) takes notice of an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> in order to encouragement. None will ſtand up to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in his behalf, though he had all Arts and Sciences lodged within the Circumference of his brain or capacity, and all Qualifications requiſit (in a Gentleman) for any
<pb facs="tcp:66102:5"/> employment publick or private, <hi>Martial</hi> or <hi>Civil;</hi> yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of inferiour parts, &amp;c. ſhall be had in far more eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſought unto, enquired for, &amp;c. The ſecond cauſe is, the ſuper-abounding ignorance and prejudicate opinion of ſome perſons Literate and illiterate, of all Functions, who know nothing as they ſhould know; and the knowledge which they cannot imitate, they hate, <hi>Nemo enim Arti inimici niſi ignorans,</hi> are born, lives and dies ignorant of all ſublime Sciences, from ſuch no encouragement is, or can be expected.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I humbly entreat You noble Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who (reads this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> and) moves in ſuperiour Sphers, that as the Almighty hath made you Patrons of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſo You would (be pleaſed to) make Your ſelves alſo Patronages of Vertue, in cheriſhing, countenancing, and encouraging of <hi>Mathematicians,</hi> aſſigning them to ſuch ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as neceſſarily falls within the limits of, and cannot otherwiſe be managed nor duly execute but by a ſubtile <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi> For the utility and benefit of the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> is of ſuch importance, that without the aſſiſtance thereof we can ſcarce live, much leſſe preſerve our ſelves from danger, or hinder the irruption of a Forreign (or Domeſtick) Enemy. And if an effectual courſe be taken with <hi>Artiſts</hi> in order to encouragement you ſhall have plurality of qualified and well skil'd <hi>Mathematicians</hi> ready to ſerve you upon all occaſions or deſignes <hi>Martial</hi> or <hi>Civil, Publick</hi> or <hi>Private,</hi> by <hi>Sea</hi> or <hi>Land,</hi> who will not only give you a true account of the Diſtances, Magnitudes and Motions of the Coeleſtial Orbs and eclipſes of the <hi>Luminaries.</hi> The probability of the Heroick Hypotheſis of <hi>Copernicus</hi> concerning the Earths motion; and ſolving the various conjectures of the Ancients concerning its ſpecies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but alſo to Meaſure, Plot, and give the true Simitry, Scituation and Content of your Land: To ſearch out all kinds of Longitudes, Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Profundities and Altitudes, acceſſible or inacceſſible to fabricate your Cities, Towns, Caſtles, Forts, Palaces and all manner of Edificis; To plant your Canons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct your Mines which rents the Rocks and tares the Earth, to the utter ruine and deſtruction of an Enemy. To trace the way of the Sun upon the Earth, and by the ſhadow of an
<pb facs="tcp:66102:5"/> Axis, to point out unto us thoſe atoms of Time unto which our artificial Day is Artificially divided, &amp;c. I think there is no Gentlman (who deſerves that denomination) that will not only deſire to learn and know theſe Arts and Sciences, but alſo confeſſe that they are moſt requiſite in all Nations, eſpecially in this moſt ancient Kingdom; but (alas) they are wanting, not becauſe of any imbicility or defect that's in our Intellectuals, for no Nation under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven can parallel us for the ſubtilty of Sciences, ſagacity of apprehenſion, &amp;c. but our only ſilence and unwillingneſs to theſe Studies that we do not profeſſe them in publique as other Nations generally do, is becauſe we want en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement.</p>
            <p>Certainly, there is no noble, liberal, or free mind of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> or <hi>Military</hi> Profeſſion, high, or low degree, of whatſoever Function or Station, but will take great delight in the Arts and Sciences Mathematical; to ſee how by Art a man can calculate the places of all the Planets, fixed Stars, and Eclipſes of the <hi>Luminaries,</hi> and that for anY <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſt, preſent, or to come. To erect Coeleſtial ſcems upon Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, framing of <hi>Aſtrological</hi> Speculums, Revolutions, Tranſits, Directions, &amp;c. To meaſure the diſtances of places remote and far aſunder, without approaching nigh them, &amp;c. theſe things are abſolutely and perfectly prodigious to vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar heads, whoſe dimmer eyes cannot penetrate the aſtral Spheres, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In all preceding ages from the Creation the <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> hath found respect and entertainment amongſt the greateſt Princes and Potentates, inſomuch that Hiſtory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports that the noble ſons of <hi>Seth</hi> were the firſt propagators of it; others, that <hi>Atlas</hi> King of <hi>Mauritania</hi> was the firſt that diſcovered the motions of the <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> and put his Invention into Writing, and afterwards commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame to his Scholer <hi>Hercules;</hi> who (as ſome Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries relate) firſt brought the Sphere into grace, whereupon aroſe that fable, <hi>Antlantem</hi> Hercules <hi>auxilio Coelum ſuſtinere humeris,</hi> but <hi>Joſephus</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> de Antiq. Jud. attributes it to the ſons of <hi>Seth,</hi> but be the Inventers of it who will, a Princely ſtudy it is, and we find many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb facs="tcp:66102:6"/> men (even Kings and Princes) in all ages to be famous therein. Nevertheleſſe, this laſt age is to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, as producing more admirable and rare diſcoveries in the admired frame and machina of the viſible world then any before had done, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But to return to my task in hand, the enſuing <hi>Treatiſe</hi> which I have entituled <hi>URANOSCOPIA,</hi> I ſeriouſly recommend to the peruſal of all ingenuous Gentlemen who (of all others) can beſt determine the worth thereof, not doubting but it will as much delight the wiſe (to whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious cenſure I freely offer it) as offend the fooliſh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the ignorant and malicious, whoſe approbation or exprobation I value not, ſtudying to approve my ſelf to God in a good Conſcience. It's my ardent affection (and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to be a ſervant to my Dread <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and to my native Countrey-men and friends, which puts the pen into my hands, elſe I ſhould have buried my Conceptions when they firſt budded: Beſides, I tremble to think what became of that ſervant who hid his Lords money in a Napkin, and did not improve it in ſuch labours as might have been for his Lords glory, profitable to himſelf and others.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, God hath endewed me with a little knowledge, eſpecially in his works of Creation, that thereby I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured (in contemplation of his works with a Sacred-ſecret delight) to know himſelf, ſo, that whatſoever I ſeek on Earth (and wants with indifferency) is all and only to be found in Heaven, where it's a honour to be a Grandee in Gods Court, to ſit on Chriſts Throne, there's glory to ſhine as the Sun, to be a brother to Saints, a peer to all Angels, a ſpouſe of the Son of God; with whom there's honour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out envie, glory without vanity, and ſtate without change. I do not call thoſe gifts little, or few, which God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon me, for that would argue (if not blaſphemy, yet) extream ingratitude; but comparatively in reſpect of that which ſhortly ſhall be revealed to the ſons of men.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if this ſmall <hi>Tract</hi> find thy candid accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it will encourage me to publiſh other things both profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and pleaſant; In the interim, if thou be deſirous of wiſdom, ask it of God, who gives it freely; be diligent and
<pb facs="tcp:66102:6"/> ſtudioas, and though thou mayeſt (perhaps) be a perſon of honour that reads this <hi>Tract,</hi> yet it will not detract a grain from thy glory, nor diminiſh thy (due) respect to be a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Sacred Coeleſtial Sciences. And although that moſt men (ſeek how they may profite and advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (making Earth their principal aim) that they may excell others) out of their blind and depraved judements, thinks that time and labour loſt that is ſpent upon the Princely Arts and Sciences <hi>Mathematical,</hi> yet there is ſome ſelect Gentlemen (whoſe inclination to vertue, makes them capable of that denomination) whom I know in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that are of more ſolid principles, and (conſidering ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly the incredible profit and excellency of the <hi>Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi>) have applyed their minds accordingly (with fixed reſolutions) to the Study of theſe noble Arts and Sciences, and are (now) become notable proficients: There may haply be many others in this Nation eminently gifted in all liberal Sciences, though they obſcure it, but its my unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I know them not, or if I do, they are perſons inacceſſible, of ſuch magnitude and altitude, that admits not of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour acceſſe, &amp;c. Wherefore I ſhall now humbly take my leave, not queſtioning but thy Courteſie will freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept what I have here communicated, having other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhortly ready to publiſh, that may witneſſe to the World how much am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>a real Friend and Servant to all honeſt Ingenious men and Arts,</hi> JAMES CORSS.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in the head of</hi> Robertſons <hi>cloſs, neer to Lady</hi> Yeſters <hi>Church in</hi> Edinb. <date>
                     <hi>April 3. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:7"/>
            <head>To my ſingularly honoured Friend Mr. <hi>Iames Corſs,</hi> upon his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> entituled, URANOSCOPIA.</head>
            <l>SIR could I dictate to <hi>Apollo's</hi> lyre,</l>
            <l>His ſacred Anthems; were my fancy high'r</l>
            <l>Then wit Meridianiz'd could feign, yet I</l>
            <l>Should juſtly fear my inſufficiency</l>
            <l>In this endeavour; for he who would praiſe</l>
            <l>Thee wel, muſt firſt court bright <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania's</hi> rayes.</l>
            <l>Dazling (yet dear) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> O that I</l>
            <l>Could once but taſte thy ſweetneſſe e're I dy!</l>
            <l>But ceaſe fond confidence, wave thoſe endeavors</l>
            <l>For bleſſed <hi>Corſs</hi> ingroſſeth all her favors,</l>
            <l>He's her <hi>Adonis,</hi> ſhe to him imparts</l>
            <l>Her ſacred Secrets, her abſtruſer Arts,</l>
            <l>By which he raiſes Monuments of Fame,</l>
            <l>Perpetuates his thriſe ingenious Name.</l>
            <l>And thou fam'd<note n="*" place="margin">The Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Glaſgow</note> Town, whoſe occidentall Towers</l>
            <l>Exults in his Production, when the powers</l>
            <l>Of rigid Fates, Illuſtrious Cities dooms</l>
            <l>To be intomb'd, within their aſhy wombs;</l>
            <l>Thou needs not fear that black oblivion ſhall</l>
            <l>Triumph upon thy glories Funerall;</l>
            <l>For while bright <hi>Titans</hi> Chariot doth run</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Corſs</hi> ſhall prove thy fam'd <hi>Mauſolium.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:7"/>
            <head>Upon my Ingenious and much honoured Friend Mr. <hi>James Corſs,</hi> his URANOSCOPIA.</head>
            <l>GReat <hi>Glaſgow's</hi> glory! Oh that I could raiſe</l>
            <l>A Monument might magnifie thy praiſe,</l>
            <l>But that's an <hi>Herculean</hi> task, yet thine</l>
            <l>Own Works have done it, thus thy praiſes ſhine</l>
            <l>Beſt from thine own Atchievements, but leſt I</l>
            <l>Shadow thy praiſe, with my obſcurity,</l>
            <l>I will be ſilent; Let who liſt aſpire</l>
            <l>To ſpeak thy praiſe, I rather will admire</l>
            <l>Thy matchleſs Arts, that makes thee ſoar ſo high</l>
            <l>To know the language of the ſpangled sky,</l>
            <l>Obſerv'ſt their order, what news their thou hears</l>
            <l>Thou tells us all, the wonders of the Spheres,</l>
            <l>Thy boundleſſe skill, with ſuch unmated glory</l>
            <l>Hath crown'd thy name, (that it's a living ſtory</l>
            <l>Of thy great worth) which may be well enrol'd</l>
            <l>Not into Paper, but rich leaves of Gold.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Mackconvy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:8"/>
            <head>Upon my honoured Friend Mr. <hi>James Corſs</hi> his URANOSCOPIA.</head>
            <l>LEt heaven and earth and all their hoſts conjoyn</l>
            <l>Their lights together, all in one light let ſhine</l>
            <l>To ſhew the glory is in aſtrall Art,</l>
            <l>That God and Nature doth to man impart,</l>
            <l>Which doth expreſſe a Divine Dialect</l>
            <l>Whoſe beams from earth to heaven it doth reflect,</l>
            <l>From worldling wit, ſuch knowledge is abſtract,</l>
            <l>But this our <hi>Author</hi> in Art is exact</l>
            <l>In ſublime manner, manifeſts his skill</l>
            <l>To <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> he doth ſhew good will,</l>
            <l>The knowledge whereof, could not be the worſs</l>
            <l>That every village had but ſuch a <hi>Corſs.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Alex. Auchmuty</hi> Philom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>A Croſtick to my Ingenious Friend Mr. <hi>Iames Corſs</hi> his URANOSCOPIA.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Ingenious ſoul, great ſounds of fame, ſets forth</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> name to thee; but far below thy worth.</l>
               <l>My lines may derogate; thy works doe praiſe,</l>
               <l>Enough thy skil and pains: for which the bayes</l>
               <l>Shall on thy head be ſet; in glorious rayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Continue then, in this thy aſtrall ſtrain;</l>
               <l>O'r looking what this Orb can give, for gain;</l>
               <l>Reſume thy works, in honour of thy Nation:</l>
               <l>So, when thou dies, &amp; hes remov'd thy Nation:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> wil ſay, thou'rt turn'd a conſtelation.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>J. Hamilton</hi> a lover of the <hi>Mathemat.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66102:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RANOSCOPIA.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAPTER I.</hi> Of the Names and Natures of the Signs, Planets and Aſpects.</head>
               <p>HE that reſolves to be an ingenious Student, or would attain any knowledge in the Sacred Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Sciences of <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> and <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> muſt (firſt) neceſſarily know that there be twelve Signs (in the Zodiack) whoſe Names and Natures are as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, Sagitary, Capricorny, Aquary</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The nature of <hi>Taurus, Virgo, Capricorny,</hi> is cold and dry, Earthly.</p>
               <p>The nature of <hi>Gemini, Libra, Aquary,</hi> is hot and moiſt, Airy.</p>
               <p>The nature of <hi>Aries, Leo, Sagitary,</hi> is hot and dry, Fiery.</p>
               <p>The nature of <hi>Cancer, Scorpio, Piſces,</hi> is cold and moiſt, Watry.</p>
               <p>The twelve ſigns are divided into Moveable, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Fixed, Maſculine and Faeminine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries, Cancer, Libra,</hi> are moveable ſigns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus, Leo, Scorpio,</hi> are fixed ſigns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gemini, Virgo, Sagitary, Piſces,</hi> are common ſigns.</p>
               <p>Maſculine ſigns be <hi>Aries, Gemini, Leo, Libra, Sagitary, Aquary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Foeinine ſigns be <hi>Taurus, Cancer, Virgo, Scorpio, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricorny, Piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Every one of theſe twelve ſigns is ſaid (and found true by experience) to rule certain diſtinct Members of Mans Body, as <hi>Aries</hi> rules the Head, <hi>Taurus</hi> the Neck, <hi>Gemini</hi> the Shoulders, <hi>Cancer</hi> the Breaſt and Ribs, <hi>Leo</hi> the Heart, <hi>Virgo</hi> the Belly and Bowels, <hi>Libra</hi> the Reins, Loyns and Kidneys, <hi>Scorpio</hi> the ſecrets of both Sexes,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66102:9"/> (tis not fitting for me to name them) <hi>Sagitary</hi> the thighs, <hi>Capricorn</hi> the Knees and Hams, and <hi>Piſces</hi> the Feet.</p>
               <p>In the twelve ſigns of the Zodiack, are conſtantly moving (according to nature) ſeven Planets, which by reaſon of their different and various motions from that of the 8 Sphere, (in which the fixed Stars move) are called wandring or erant Stars, whoſe Names and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are theſe following, viz. <hi>Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus, Mercurius,</hi> and the <hi>Moon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe 7 Planets, two (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi>) are moſt perſpicuous and univerſally known, by every vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar eye, but the other five are carefully obſerved (only) by the Sons of Wiſdom, in all ages throughout the earth.</p>
               <p>The ſeven Planets are of different Natures, for</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> is cold and dry, and hath <hi>Capricorny</hi> and <hi>Aquary</hi> for his houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> is hot and moiſt, and hath <hi>Sagitary</hi> and <hi>Piſces</hi> for his houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> is hot and dry, and hath <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Scorpio</hi> for his houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> is hot and dry, and hath only <hi>Leo</hi> for his houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> is cold and moiſt, and hath <hi>Taurus</hi> and <hi>Libra</hi> for her houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> is convertible in nature, and hath <hi>Gemini</hi> and <hi>Virgo</hi> for his houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luna</hi> is cold and moiſt, and hath only <hi>Cancer</hi> for her houſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſeven Planets moving in the twelve ſigns, do make ſeveral Angles and mutual Aſpects, from whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, the generation and corruption of all Sublunaries are cauſed, and they are five eſpecially, whoſe Names, and Natures are theſe following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Conjunction</hi> is either good or bad.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Sextile</hi> is an aſpect of imperfect friendſhip.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Quartile</hi> is imperfect enmity.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Trine</hi> ſignifies perfect amity.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Oppoſition</hi> ſignifies nothing but miſchief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus much ſhall ſerve for the Names and Natures of the Signs, Planets and Aſpects.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66102:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of ſeveral Terms of Art, neceſſary for all Students to underſtand.</head>
               <p>BEſides the Names and Natures of the Signs, Planets and Aſpects, which I ſhewed you before, there are ſome other Terms of Art (uſed by <hi>Aſtronomers</hi>) which ſeem difficult to be underſtood, unleſſe firſt explained, as Applications, Separations, Prohibitions, Peregrinations, Retrogradations, Combuſtions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Planets.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Aspects</hi> of the Planets are either partile or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique. A partile <hi>Aſpect</hi> is when Planets behold one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly to the ſame degree and minut, be it either <hi>Sextile, Quartile, Trine</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition:</hi> But a platique <hi>Aſpect</hi> is, when Planets are within the mediety of others Orbs, which Orbs are as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Orbs of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saturn</hi> are 10 deg. 00 min.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jupiter</hi> are 12 deg. 00 min.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mars</hi> are 7 deg. 30 min.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sol</hi> are 17 deg. 00 min.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> are 8 deg. 00 min.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mercurius</hi> are 7 deg. 00 min.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Luna</hi> are 12 deg. 00 min.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Their's <hi>Application</hi> of Planets, and that 3 wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, When two Planets (both direct and in motion, and the one a more light and ſwifter Planet then the other) do apply. As <hi>Mercurius</hi> in 10 deg. of <hi>Aries,</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> in 10 deg. of <hi>Gemini,</hi> here <hi>Mercury</hi> (being more ſwift then <hi>Saturn</hi>) is ſaid to apply to a <hi>Sextile</hi> of him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, When both Planets is Retrograde.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when one Planet is direct (in motion) and the other Retrograde, as <hi>Mercury</hi> Retrograde in 10 deg. of <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> direct in 15 deg. of <hi>Aries, Mercury</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid to apply to the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> by Retrogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation.</p>
               <p>Here note, that the Superiour Planets (<hi>Saturn, Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi>) never apply (unleſſe Retrograde) to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66102:10"/> Inferiours; but (juſt as it is amongſt men) the Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours alwayes apply unto the Superiours. This Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Oeconomy demonſtrates the infinit love of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, who being <hi>Superiorum Altiſſimus,</hi> ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to us, his ſinful creatures, even when we run Retrograde. O wonderful love!</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Separation</hi> of Planets is, when two Planets having been united by Body or Aſpect, and are ſeparated or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from each other ſix minuts at leaſt, continuing their ſeparations, untill they be paſt the mediety of others Orbs.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Prohibition</hi> of Planets is twofold: Firſt, When two Planets are applying to each other, but before they can come to eithers Body or Aſpect, behold another Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ſwifter in motion, interpoſes his Rayes, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits their Application. Secondly, When a lighter Planet is applying to another (Planet) more ponderous, and before he comes to his Body or Aſpect, falls Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade, and ſo is prevented by that Planets refrenation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of light and nature is, when a light Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ſhall ſeparate from a more weighty one, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly ſhall be joyned to a more ponderous one.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Reception</hi> of Planets is, when they are mutually in others Houſes, Exaltations, Triplicities, Terms, or Faces.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Peregrime,</hi> a Planet is ſaid to be Peregrine, when he is out of all his eſſential dignities.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Fruſtration</hi> is, when a light Planet would joyn with another more ponderous; but before he can come to the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of him, the ponderous Planet is joyned to another, whereby the <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the firſt with him is fruſtrated.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Combuſtion</hi> is, when a Planet is within 8 degrees, 30 minuts of the Suns Body: here note, that a Planet is more afflicted when he is applying to (then ſeparat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from) combuſtion.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Cazimini,</hi> Planets are ſaid to be in <hi>Cazimini</hi> or <hi>(Cordiſolis)</hi> heart of the <hi>Sun,</hi> until they be ſeparated 17 min. from his Body, all Planets in <hi>Cazimini</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly fortified.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66102:10"/>11. <hi>Direction,</hi> Planets are ſaid to be direct in motion, when they move a regular progreſſe in the Sign they are in, as out of one degree into another, and from that to the third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Retrogradation</hi> is, when Planets move contrary to their wonted order and ſucceſſion, and goes back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as out of the eight degree into the ſeventh, and ſo to the ſixth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Planets</hi> are ſaid to be Stationary, when they move not at all, but ſtands ſtill in the Heavens.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Planets are ſaid to be <hi>Oriental,</hi> when they riſe before the Sun, &amp; <hi>Occidental</hi> when they ſet after the Sun.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Beſieging</hi> is, when a Planet is between the Bodies of two other Planets, if the Beſiegers be benevolents, its good, otherwiſe its (almoſt) as bad as Combuſtion.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Planets are ſaid to be void of Cauſe, when they are ſeparated from a Planet, and do not apply unto, nor meet with the Body or Aſpect of another, during the time they be (and remain) in the Sign wherein they are poſited. This accident happens moſt frequently to the <hi>Moon,</hi> by reaſon of her firſt motion, this much ſhall ſerve for the Terms of Art, and their Explanations, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Young Beginner ought to be acquainted with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Syſtemn of the World, and Motion of the Earth,</head>
               <p>THe World (containing all the Viſible Creation) is the order and diſtribution of all things kept and preſerved of God, and is vulgarly divided into two parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Heaven and Earth, of which this Excellent Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture is compoſed. The Center of which Fabrick is held to be the Sun; but their hath been much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie amongſt the moſt eminent <hi>Mathematicians</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Scituation and Motion of the Sun and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66102:11"/> Earth. <hi>Copernicus</hi> and ſome of the Ancients, before and ſince Chriſt, held the Sun to be immovably fixed in the Center of the Univerſs, and that it was the Earth (only) that moved: Others again denied, affirming that the Sun moves only, and that the Earth ſtands ſtill. Both produce their Reaſons and Demonſtrations to prove it. The Judgement of <hi>Divines</hi> is unanimous, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Earth is immovably fixed, and that its the Sun that moves. But although the Judgement of <hi>Divines</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in it, yet I am not altogether of their Opinion, that ſaith it is immoveably fixed in the Center. For the equal (or unequal) diſtribution of the Univerſal <hi>Anima Mundi,</hi> alloweth it to have a Life: and conſequently Motion (which is the property of Life (and therefore it muſt be granted, that either their's no ſuch thing, as the Univerſal <hi>Anima Mundi:</hi> or elſe if there be that the Earth is exempt of it and ſo lifeleſſe, to affirm either of which is prodigiouſly abſurd and ridiculous, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Judgement of the ſoundeſt <hi>Divines, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> and <hi>Mathematicians.</hi> But whether the Earths Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be Central, Circular, or Equilibral, their's the Queſtion, let them whet their Wits upon it, and they will be the ſharper. As for me, I ſhall ſatisfie my parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular friends concerning the Motion thereof; (for I am confident it hath a Motion, though inſenſible, by reaſon of the diſ-proportion, which our viſual ſenſes have to its vaſt Magnitude) and the World in general in the next Edition.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall now return to give you an account of the ſeveral Spheres of Heaven, in their various Situations and Motions, according to the Opinion, Demonſtration, and acurate Obſervations of that <hi>Noble Daniſh Lord, Tycho Brahe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Earth is the Center of the World, equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtant in all places from the vaſt Circumference of the fixed Stars.</p>
               <p n="2">2. About the Earth is the Sphere of the Moon, which by reaſon of its Propinquity and Parvity of her Orbe, She compleateth her Periodical Revolution in a Month.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66102:11"/>3. The Sun is the Center of the Planetary Syſtemn, ſo that all the Planets reſpect Him as their common Node and Center, He compleateth His Courſe through the twelve Signs of the Zodiack in a year.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The neareſt Planet to the Sun, is the Orbe of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> which by reaſon of the Parvity of his Circle and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinity to the Sun (his greateſt Elongation not exceeding 28 degrees) therefore he is rarely ſeen, he finiſheth his Revolution in 88 dayes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the next Sphere moves <hi>Venus,</hi> who accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her Revolution through the 12 Signs of the Zodiack in 225 dayes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The next Sphere above the Orbe of the Sun, is the Orbe of <hi>Mars,</hi> which Interſects the Suns Orbe twice, he compleateth his Revolution once in two years.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The next Sphere above the Orbe of <hi>Mars,</hi> is <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> he finiſheth his Revolution in 12 years.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The higheſt of all the Planetary Spheres, is the Sphere of <hi>Saturn,</hi> who by reaſon of his great Remotion from the Earth, and Center of the Univerſs, compleats his Revolution but once in 30 years.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And laſtly, Above the Sphere of <hi>Saturn,</hi> is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Orbe of the Firmament, wherein all the fixed Stars are placed, which compleateth its Revolution it 25920. years.</p>
               <p>Having now ſpoken of the Coeleſtial <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Planetarie Spheres, even from the Center to the vaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Circumference, I am drowned in a Sea of Admiration and Contemplation, to behold, and ſeriouſly conſider (with a Secret ſacred delight) the Proportion, Scituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Magnitude, Tranſcendant Glory and Luſter, Stupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and Conſtant Order of the Viſible Coeleſtial Hoſts of Almighty God, <hi>Cujus Centrum eſt ubique, Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia nullubi.</hi> I can never behold and contemplate them ſooner, then my Heart and Soul is lifted above the Heavens, by the raviſhing ſight of JEHOVAHS back parts, which conducts me thither by Inviſible Lines, and Immortal Beams, am led in to the moſt Holy Place, where the KING in His Beauty, the ANCIENT
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66102:12"/> of DAYES ſits upon His Throne, attended by Infinit Millions of Saints and Angels (whoſe Glory obſcures the Viſible Sun) ſounding everlaſting Anthems to the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum cus.</hi> The firſt beginning and ultimate end of all Created Beings, The Supreme UNITY of all Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. I ſay, when I conſider theſe things, my ſouls joy Initiats.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O my dear God, comfort my ſoul and heart with thy Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Rayes, and ſtrengthen the underſtanding of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with a Light of Glory, that may enable me to bear thy Beatifical Viſions. For I am raviſhed in Contemplation of thy Glorious Works of Creation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Eclipſes of the Sun and Moon.</head>
               <p>AS there is no part of the Mathematicks ſo Noble and Excellent as Aſtronomy: So there is no part of Aſtronomy ſo difficult as the Doctrine of the Eclipſes (eſpecially when the Calculation of Solar Eclipſes is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and determined to a certain Longitude and Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) in regard of the tedious Computation of the Moons Paralaxes in Longitude and Latitude (upon which the Solar Eclipſe principally depends. This Peece of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is the very Superſtructure and Punctilio of Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and ſo rare is it to be found amongſt men, that not one of 20000. hath attain'd to it, it is the very Crown and higheſt Pitch (and may juſtly Challenge to it ſelf the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and Precedency) of all Humane Learning what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. 'Tis not only Speculative (for the Ignorant) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Contemplative (for the Ingenious) but alſo Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive (becauſe it tells us as well what Eclipſes is paſt, as what's to come) In ſo much, that an Aſtronomer is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Angel, then a man, and (at leaſt) a Prophet in the Superlative Degree. Is there any Art or Science under Heaven (except Aſtronomy) that can tell me, Whether
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66102:12"/> there will be any Eclipſes of the Luminaries in <hi>March, Anno Chriſti,</hi> 1990. Or (I might have ſaid) 5670? (Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſing the World ſhall continue ſo long) Can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Philoſophy, Phyſick, or Logick do 't? No it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, and yet an Aſtronomer will reſolve the Queſtion within one quarter of an hour, almoſt, <hi>Ex tempore.</hi> And is not this a rare Art, and Worthy to be Encouraged, but the blind World knows little the Sublimity of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks. And hence it is that they alwayes bewray their own Ignorance, by proportioning their Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accordingly. But to return,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Eclipſes of the Luminaries are (vulgarly accounted) twofold, <hi>viz.</hi> Solar and Lunar. The Solar Eclipſe is cauſed by the Interpoſition of the Moon, between the Sun and the Earth, whereby ſome particular Tract of the Earth is deprived of the Suns Light, during the Eclipſe, at which time other places of the World, have the full light of the Sun. The Lunar Eclipſe is cauſed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of the Earth, between the Sun and Moon: ſo that the ſhaddow of the Earth falls directly upon the Moon, and thence comes the obſcurity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Eclipſes of the Sun are alwayes happening at the Change of the Moon, and Eclipſes of the Moon happen at the full Moon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Magnitude of every Eclipſe depends upon the Propinquity of the Moon to the Ecliptick Dragons Head or Tail.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When the new Moon is Central; and falls exactly in either of the Nods, the full Moon next preceeding and ſucceeding, do alwayes paſſe without an Eclipſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When there be two Central new Moons, the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Suns Apogaeon, the other after, there ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen no full Moon Eclipſe that year.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When there are two full Moons in ſix Months ſpace, in, or near the Ecliptick Line, it uſually falls out, that there will be no Eclipſes of the Sun that year, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they cannot be of any ſenſible Magnitude, neither be viſible in any part of the World, but only near the Poles.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66102:13"/>7. Eclipſes of the Moon are Univerſal, appearing in all places (where it's viſible) of a like Quantity and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, differing only in Time, according to the Meridian of the place.</p>
               <p n="8">8. A Reduction for the difference of Meridians, will give the time of the appearance of a Lunar Eclipſe, to any determinate place of the Earth.</p>
               <p n="9">9. At the mean time of the full Moon, if the midle Longitude of the Moon ſhall be different from the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons Head or Tail, leaſt then 15 deg. 12 min. either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording or contrary to the ſucceſſion of Signs, then that full Moon will be eclipſed, but if more ſhe will not.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Eclipſes of the Sun is different in every Climate, ſo as the neither retain the ſame Time, Quantity nor Duration in all places alike, and therefore admits not of any Reduction.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Eclipſes of the Sun will only agree to that deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate place of the Earth, for which they are calculated to a certain Longitude and Latitude, becauſe of the Moons Vicinity to the Earth, and ſudden changes of her Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxes in Longitude and Latitude.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The Conical Shaddow of the Earth, terminating in a Point (in a Lunar Eclipſe) is augmented or diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, according to the Suns Propinquity to, or Remotion from the Earth.</p>
               <p n="13">13. At the mean time of a new Moon, if the midle mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Moons Latitude ſhall be diſtant from the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons Head leſſe then 20 deg. 40 min. or from the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons Tail, leſſe then a 11 deg. 22 min. then the Sun will be eclipſed of that Conjunction, but if more he cannot.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Eclipſes of the Luminaries, forwarns this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full World of Drought, Inundation of Waters, Wars, Plagues and Peſtilences, Famine, and the Viſiſitude of all Sublunaries.</p>
               <p>I have compoſed an Almanack for ſeven years to come, initiating <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 1663. terminating 1669. Not a Tranſcript, but a Calculation <hi>de novo,</hi> for the Meridian of the moſt famous City of <hi>Glaſgow.</hi> Whither or no I have had great pains in its Calculation, either in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66102:13"/> Eclipſes of the Luminaries, or Monthly Lunations, he (only) ſhall know that ſhall attempt, to do the like. I have Typified all the Eclipſes that wil be Viſible in Great Britain, during theſe ſeven years, the greateſt Eclipſe of the Sun that happens within the time (aforeſaid) is upon <hi>May</hi> the 15 day, 1668. The Type whereof as it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the Heavens, in the Meridian of the City of <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow,</hi> take as followeth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of an ecliptic</figDesc>
                  <p>EAST</p>
                  <p>NORTH</p>
                  <p>WEST</p>
                  <p>SOUTH</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66102:14"/>
               <p>The Explanation of the Figure is this, H, I, L, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the Ecliptique, wherein the Sun continually moves, I, is the Center of the Sun, A, the Center of the Moon at the beginning of the Eclipſe, V, is her Center and true Place at the Viſible Conjunction: At which time ſo much of the dark Body of the Moon as covereth the Sun in this Figure: ſo much of the Suns Body in the Heavens will be covered by the Inrerpoſition of the Moons dark Body, between the Sun and the Citizens of <hi>Glaſgow:</hi> E, is the place of the Moon at the end of the Eclipſe, when the utter Circles of the two Luminaries, laſtly touch one another. The Line, A, V E, repreſents the way of the Moon, during the time of the Eclipſe; but for further ſatisfaction in the Premiſes, I refer you to the Book it ſelf, which will be ere long Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>If you deſire to behold an Eclipſe of the Sun without damage to the Eyes,</head>
                  <p>THen take a Burning-glaſſe, ſuch as men uſe to light Tobacco with the Sun; or a Spectacle-glaſſe that is thick in the midle, ſuch as is for the eldeſt ſight, and hold this Glaſſe in the Sun as if you would burn through it a Paſtboard of White-paper-book, or ſuch like; and draw the Glaſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>om the Board or Book, twice ſo far as you do to burn with it: ſo by direct holding it nearer or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as you ſhall ſee beſt, you may behold upon your Board, Paper, or Book, the round body of the Sun, and how the Moon paſſeth between the Glaſſe and the Sun during the whole time of the Eclipſe.</p>
                  <p>This mayeſt thou practiſe before the time of an Eclipſe wherein thou ſhalt diſcern any Cloud paſſing under the Sun; or by another putting or holding a Bullet on his fingers end betwixt the Sun and the Glaſſe at ſuch time (the Sun ſhining) as thou holdeſt the Glaſſe, as before thou art taught.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:66102:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> To find how long the Effects of an Eclipſe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, and when they begin and end.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ot horas durat Eclipſis Solaris tot annorum duratoris, effectus praenunciat: Quot horas durat Lunaris ut menſem.</hi> How many hours the Sun is Eclipſed, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years will the effects continue, but if it be a Lunar Eclipſe, ſo many Months.</p>
               <p>Now to find the time when the effects of ſome Eclipſe begins and ends, obſerve if the Eclipſe falls in the Eaſtern Horizon, the effects thereof will manifeſt themſelves, about the next four Months following the Eclipſe, and will more ſtrongly operate in the firſt third part of its whole Duration — But if it fall in the Mid-heaven, the Events thereof will begin to appear in the 4th Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth next following, but moſt apparent will the effects be in the middle moſt third part of its whole Duration. — But if it happen in the Weſt part of the Horizon, the effects ſhall not begin untill about the laſt four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and its greateſt Operation will be in the laſt third part of its whole Duration.</p>
               <p>Therefore we are to obſerve at the midle of the Eclipſe, how far the Luminary eclipſed is diſtant from the riſing, and how long it continueth above the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon: which known, reduce them into minuts (for faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Operation) and then ſay by the Golden Rule — if the time of the whole continuance of the Luminary eclipſed above the Horizon, give 365 dayes (or a whole year) What ſhall the time of the riſing give? Multiply and Divide, and the Quotient will yeeld your deſire.</p>
               <p>As for example, in the Eclipſe of the Moon that is to happen the 27 of <hi>July</hi> 1664. (in the Meridian of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Famous City of <hi>Glaſgow</hi>) at a 11 hours, 12 min. 12 ſeconds. The Moons Nocturnal Arch is 8 hours, 30 min. reduced into minuts is 510.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:66102:15"/>
               <p>The Sun ſets (in the Latitude of 56 deg.) at 45 min. paſt 7. which in this caſe may ſerve for the time of the Moons riſing: ſo that the diſtance of the Moon at the greateſt Obſcuration, is 3 hours, 37 min. which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced (as aforeſaid) into minuts, is 217.</p>
               <p>Now 365 (the dayes in a Common Year) multiplied by 217. the product 79205. divided by 510. the Quotient is 155. 31—102. Or you may perform the Operation with more facility and greater expedition by the <hi>Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmes,</hi> which was firſt invented by the thrice noble and Illiſtruous Lord, viz. <hi>John Lord Nepper, Barron of Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe Name and Fame will never Terminate, until the general Diſſolution.</p>
               <p>The Operations, by his <hi>Lagarithmes,</hi> is this,
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Logarith.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Length of the night, 8 h. 30 m. or 510 m.</cell>
                        <cell>2, 707570</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Common Year hath 365 dayes.</cell>
                        <cell>2, 562293</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Diſtance of the greateſt obſcuration, 3 h. 37 m. or 217 m.</cell>
                        <cell>2, 336459</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4, 898752</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Dayes or the Effects begin. 155.</cell>
                        <cell>2, 161182</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo many dayes it will be, before the Effects begin to operate, and therefore from the day of the Eclipſe, (<hi>viz.</hi> the 27 of <hi>July,</hi> 1664.) I number 155 dayes, and it points out the 29. of <hi>December</hi> following, on which day the Eclipſe begins to Operate. And becauſe the Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaids Eclipſe is 4 h. 1 m. 8 ſ. (according to my Doctrine of Eclipſes) therefore the Effects will laſt 4 Months, from the 29 of <hi>December</hi> 1664. as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>Ptolomy</hi> ſaith, that how many hours the Sun is diſtant from the Horoſcope (or aſcendant, all's one) at the time of his Eclipſe, ſo many years will it be ere the Effects begin to Operate: ſo that if the Eclipſe be in or near the Weſt Angle, it may be 12 whole years, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Effects take place: But I rather conſent to <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganus,</hi> who ſaith, they Inchoate at the very day of the Eclipſe. <hi>Conſentem namque eſt Eclipſes ſtatim operari, &amp; effectus ſuos aliquaſque extendere. Orig. par.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de effectibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66102:15"/>
               <p>Thus having ſhown you how to find the time of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ending of the Effects of the Eclipſes and time of continuance, I come next to ſhew in what Kingdoms and Countreys the Effects will principally manifeſt themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Names of the Regions, Cities and Towns, ſubject to the Signs and Planets.</head>
               <p>THe Effects of Eclipſes are moſt felt in thoſe Regions and places that are under the eclipſed Sign, and in ſuch places where they are viſible, <hi>Nil nocet Eclipſis illis Regionibus, in quibus non videtur:</hi> They operate more efficaciouſly in ſuch places where they are Vertical, or where the chief Significator ſhall paſſe by their Zenith in the time of the Eclipſe. As alſo upon thoſe men whoſe Nativities agreeth with the Eclipſe, that is to ſay, upon them in whoſe Nativity or Revolution have the place of the Horoſcope (ſome ignorant fantaſtick fools cannot indure this word <hi>Horoſcope</hi>) becauſe it's above the reach of their capacities; for their ignorance outweighs their Wits, as much as a Milſtone a Feather: They hate all they underſtand not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore they may call it (if they pleaſe) the Aſcendant, for all's one) Sun, Moon, part of Fortune, and other Planets in, or about the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the Eclipſe, or in <hi>Quartile,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> thereof. Eſpecially if there be any Malevolent Direction concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therewith. But to return,</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are theſe Regions.</head>
                  <p>England, France, Germany, Swevia, Sileſia the higher, Polonia the leſſe, Denmark, Syria, Paleſtina, and of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Towns, Naples and Comia, Capua, Feraria, Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, Verona, Lindavia, Rajectum, Padua, Brunſwick, Cracovia, Vincentium.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:66102:16"/>
                  <head>Under <hi>Taurus</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Ruſſia, Polonia the Great, Ireland, Lorain, Campania, Helvetia, Rhetia, Franconia, Parthea, Perſia, the Iſlands of Syclades, Cyprus and the Sea Towns of Aſia the leſs; of Cities and Towns, Bononia, Sena, Mantua, Tarentum, Sicilie, Parma, Brixia, Tigor, Lacern, Nantz, Lipſig, Poſnania, Gueſna.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Gemini</hi> and <hi>Mercuri,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Sardinia, part of Lombardie, Flanders, Brabant, the Dukedome of Wertemberge, Hercania, Armenia, Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naica, and Egypt the lower; of Cities and Towns, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Corduba, Turinum, Vercelas, Lovain, Bruges in Flanders, Moguntia, Bamberge, Norrinberge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Cancer</hi> and the <hi>Moon,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Scotland, Granado, Burgundia, the lower Holland, Zealand, Ruſſia, Numidia, Africa, Bythinia, Phrygia, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſh, Carthage; of Cities and Towns, Conſtantinople, Tunnis, Venice, Genoa, Luce, Piſa, Millain, Vinſcentia, Bern, York, St. Andrews, Lubeck, Magdeberg, Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, Gorlick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Leo</hi> and the <hi>Sun.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Gallia, Togata, the Alps, Italy, Sicily, Apuliae, Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, a part of Turkie, Phenicia, Caldea; and of Cities and Towns, Damaſcus, Syrabuſa, Rome, Ravena, Cremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Ulms, Confluens, Pragu, Lintz, Cremiſum.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Virgo</hi> and <hi>Mercuri,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Achaja, Greece, Crete, Corinthia, Artheſina, a part of Galia, Comata a part of the Rhyne, Sileſiia the lower, Meſopotamia, Babylon, Aſſyria; and of Cities and Towns, Jeruſalem, Corinth, Novaria, Brunduſium, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, Tholos, Lyons, Paris, Baſil, Heidlberg, Erphord, Uratiſlavia.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Libra</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Auſtria, Alſatia, Livonia, Sabodia, Delphinate, Thuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Bactriana, Caſpia, Thebys, Togloditica; and of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Towns, Liſborn, Arles, Cajeta, Lauda, Laſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina, Friburg, Argentina, Spires, Frankford upon Moene, Hallinſwevia, Heilbrune, Phryſinga, Moſbachum, Vyena in Auſtria, Antwarp.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:66102:16"/>
                  <head>Under <hi>Scorpia</hi> and <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Norway the higher, Bavaria, Comagena, Capadocia, Edumea, Mauritania, Catholinia, the Kingdom of Feſs, Getulia; and of Cities and Towns, Algeirs, Valens, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pezunt, Urbinum, Acquilia, Piſtorium, Terviſtum, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum-Julium, Meſſana, Vienna in France, Monachium, Franckford upon Odar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Sagitary</hi> and <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Spain, Dalmatia, Slavonia, Hungary, Marravia, Miſnia, Seltica, Arabia the happy; of Cities and Towns, Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Voba-Terras, Mutinum, Narbone, Avenion, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Aggrippina, Slagarde, Buda.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Capricorn</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Macedonia, Ilyrus, Thratia, Albania, Bulgaria, part of Greece, Muſovia, Lituania, Saxania, Haſcia, Thuringia, Stiria, India, and the Iſlands of Arcadias; and of Cities and Towns, Oxford, Juliacum, Clivia, Berges, Mechlin, Gaunt, Vilna, Brandeburge, Auguſta, Vindel, Conſtance, Fervence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Aquary</hi> and <hi>Saturn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Amazania, Samaria, Great Tartaria, Valachia, Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, the ſouth-part of Swedland, Weſtphalia, Moſel, Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, part of Bavaria, Ethiopia, Sogdiana, Media, Arabia the Deſart; of Cities and Towns, Hamburg, Breme, Monſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferat, Piſaurum, Trentim, Golſtead.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Under <hi>Piſces</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Cilicia, Calabria, Pottugal, Galitia, Normandi, Garo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantes, Lydia, Pamphilia, Egypt the higher; of Cities and Towns, Alexandria, Hiſpalis, Compoſtella, Worms, Ratiſbon, Tevertoun.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> To Prognoſticate the Natural Portents of Eclipſes.</head>
               <p>FIrſt erect your ſcheme exactly to the time of the midle (or greateſt obſcuration) of the Eclipſe, then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66102:17"/> conſider diligently what Planet is Lord of that Eclipſe, by colecting the eſſential Dignities and Debilities of the Planets from the aſcendant, <hi>Medium Coeli,</hi> and place defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, &amp;c. And ſeeing experience in all ages teſtifieth that Eclipſes of the Luminaries hath been attended with ſome notable events, and ſequels, as not only Hiſtories, but even our Times do teſtifie. I ſhall therefore inſert a few Aphoriſmes (built upon Experience) by which the natural portents of Eclipſes may be foretold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhall happen to be Lord of an Eclipſe, he portends much evil, Corruption proceeding from cold, tedious diſeaſes, Conſumptions, Feavers, Dropſies, Fears, Exiles, &amp;c. and in the Air he engenders thick pitchy Clouds, Snow, Shipwracks, ſcarcity of Fruit, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury, damage by Locuſts, Hail and violent Storms.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If <hi>Jupiter</hi> be Lord of an Eclipſe, he cauſes things to encreaſe, giveth good things, and is the general ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifier of Peace and Tranquility, when he alone beareth principal rule, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If <hi>Mars</hi> be Lord of an Eclipſe, he preſageth Wars, Tumults, Diſſentions, Violence, Injury, great Heat, Tempeſts, Lightning and Dryneſſe; he brings upon men Impriſonments, Captivities, threatens Depopulations and Slaughters of men, beſides many ſore and grievous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, and much evil in general.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If <hi>Venus</hi> be principal ruler of an Eclipſe, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth much good to enſue, and promiſeth a delicate and temperate ſeaſon, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If <hi>Mercury</hi> be Lord of an Eclipſe, he doth inſinuate himſelf into the nature of that Planet he is joyned with, or aſpected to: Of his own nature, he portends dry Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, Coughs, Quotidian Feavers, he ſignifieth Roberies and Pyratical Invaſions, he moveth turbulent Winds, brings Dryneſſe, Thunders, Lightning, and hurts the Fruits of the Earth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In prognoſticating the effects of the Eclipſes, the Aſteriſm in which the Eclipſe happeneth, is to be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily obſerved: For if it ſhall repreſent the form of men, then the influence will fall chiefly upon men; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66102:17"/> four footed beaſts, upon four footed beaſts; if Serpents, upon Serpents.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If there happen an Eclipſe (eſpecially of the Sun) and <hi>Mars</hi> be the principal ruler thereof, and poſited in a fiery or airy ſign, <hi>Mars</hi> being ſtrong and Lord of the year; It threatens Houſe burnings.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If <hi>Saturn</hi> be Lord of the place Eclipſed, and be ſtrong in earthly or watry Signes, <hi>Mars</hi> being joyned to Stars of <hi>Saturns</hi> nature, or if he be in Conjunction, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, or Oppoſition to <hi>Saturn,</hi> it portends an Earthquake, and Inundations.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In Prognoſticating the effects of the Eclipſes, you are to obſerve in what Houſe of Heaven the Luminarie Eclipſed (or the Eclipſe it ſelf) happens in, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of that Eclipſe will moſt ſtrongly operate upon thoſe men and things ſignified by that Houſe.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Fiunt in mundo multa in commoda quando erit in una menſe utriuſque Luminaris Eclipſis, &amp; praecipue in his locis quibus eſt ſignificatio eorum speciales.</hi> Herms. <hi>Centi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquium</hi> 53.</p>
               <p>And thus much ſhall ſerve for judging the effects of the Eclipſes for any time coming. I come next to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate how,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> To finde the Lords of the Year, and four Quarters thereof.</head>
               <p>THe beſt way as <hi>Origanus</hi> ſaith, is to erect three Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures for every Quarter. viz. one for the <hi>Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of the Luminaries preceeding the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, the next for the Ingreſſe it ſelf, and the third for the <hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> ſuccceding it, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Haly</hi> himſelf was of another opinion as appears, <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>de Jud.</hi> Aſtrorum (to whom <hi>Guido</hi> aſſents, <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 24.) <hi>Quando introitu ſolis in arietem fuerit aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66102:18"/> ſignum fixum continet enim illa Revolution, in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quartas illius anni &amp; ſic qui fuerit tunc Dominus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, erit Dominus totius anni, &amp; totius Revolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ionis illius, ſed ſi fuerit aſcendens ſignum Commune, non durabit illa Revolutio, niſi uſque ad introitum Sol in Libram, tunc op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portebit te reiterare Revolutionem,</hi> &amp;c. When at the Suns ingreſſe into <hi>Aries,</hi> if the Sign aſcending ſhall be a fixed Sign, that <hi>Revolution</hi> comprehends in it ſelf, all the four Quarters of that year, and ſo he that ſhall (then) be found Lord, ſhall be Lord of the whole year, and of that whole Revolution, &amp;c. but I rather adhere to <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomy, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Quadr. cap.</hi> 10. who adviſeth us to erect Schems of the four Quarters, and of the preceeding <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of the Luminaries, and ſo raiſe a judgement of the ſtate and condition of the year; I my ſelf do alwayes follow this Direction: For I erect four Figures for the ingreſſe of the Sun into the cardinal Signs, <hi>Aries, Cancer, Libra, Capricorny,</hi> and to the time of the Lunations preceeding and ſucceeding the Suns ingreſſe into theſe Signs; and ſo I collect the eſſentiall Debilities and Dignities of the Planets from the Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope <hi>Medium Coeli,</hi> and places of the Luminaries. Laſtly, that Planet which I find to excell in teſtimonies of Fortitude, I conclude him chief Almuten and Ruler of that Revolution.</p>
               <p>In like manner I find out the Lord of an Eclipſe, by collecting the eſſential Dignities and Debilities from the Horoſcope, <hi>Medium Coeli,</hi> and place deficient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the ſignification of the twelve Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Houſes.</head>
               <p>THere are four principal parts of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> two of which fall equally upon the Horizon, and the other two upon the Meridian, theſe are called Cardinal
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66102:18"/> Points, or Angles of the Figure, viz. The aſcendant <hi>Medium Coeli,</hi> the Angle of the Weſt, and <hi>Imum Coeli;</hi> thoſe Houſes that next follow theſe Angles be the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, fifth, eighth, and eleventh, and are called Succe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. The third, ſixt, fourth, and twelfth are called Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and does preceed the four Angles.</p>
               <p>The firſt Houſe hath proper ſignification of any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives Life, Stature, Form, Shape, Viſage, Temperature, Complexion and Colour, and is called the Horoſcope, Aſcendant, or Angle Orient.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Houſe; of Eſtate, Goods moveable or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, and is called of the Greeks <hi>Anaphora,</hi> from the continual Aſcenſions of the Planets (there) to the Eaſt.</p>
               <p>The third Houſe; of Brethren, Siſters, Kindred, Neighbours, Removals, or in land Journeys, Epiſtles, Letters, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The fourth Houſe; Lands, Houſes, Tenements, Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritances, Patrimony, the natives Father, &amp;c. its called <hi>Imum Coeli.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifth Houſe, Children, their condition and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, Delights, Muſick, Mirth, Banquetings, Playes and Games, Meſſengers, Ambaſſadors, the fathers ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſixth Houſe, of all manner of Diſeaſes that our frail Nature is ſubject to, their Quality and Cauſe, Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Incurability, Servants, ſmal Beaſts.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Houſe, of Marriage, Law-ſuits, Publick Enemies, Conteſts, Duels, Controverſies, Partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The eighth Houſe, of Death, Goods of dead Men, Legacies, Wills, Womens Dowries, <hi>Nulla diviſio circuli tunc peſſima tamque crudelis in omnibus quam octava eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ninth Houſe, of Religion, long Journeys, Dreams, Viſions of all Arts and Sciences, the Wifes Kindred, Church-men and Lawyers, all Ingenious men whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p>The tenth Houſe of Preferment, Office, Honour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, Vocation, or Trade the Mother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It's called
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66102:19"/> 
                  <hi>Medium Coeli,</hi> or <hi>Cor Coeli,</hi> the mid Heaven, or Heart of Heaven.</p>
               <p>The eleventh Houſe of Friends, Favourites and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, it's called <hi>Bonus Genius,</hi> or good <hi>Daemon,</hi> Angel or Spirit.</p>
               <p>The twelfth Houſe of Impriſonments, Captivities, Baniſhments, Private Enemies, great Cattel, as Oxen, Horſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And this much ſhall ſerve for the general ſignification of the twelve Houſes, which is more briefly comprehended in theſe few Verſes.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Prima domus, vitam largitur, &amp; altera nummos,</l>
                  <l>Tertia dat fratres, Venerandos quarta Parentes,</l>
                  <l>Prolem quinta dabit. Morbos tibi ſexta minatur,</l>
                  <l>Septima conjugii domus eſt, octavaque Mortis,</l>
                  <l>Religio ſequitur, confert tibi decima honores,</l>
                  <l>Hinc tibi amicus erit, poſtremam inimicus habebit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Or more briefly thus,
<q>
                     <l>Vita, Lucrum, Fratres, Genitor, Nati, Valetudo,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor, Mors Pietas, Regnum, Benefactaque, Carcer.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of the Diſtances, Magnitudes and Colours of the ſeven Planets.</head>
               <p>THere hath been much controverſie amongſt the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Mathematicians, concerning the Planets juſt Magnitude and Diſtance, the very Dimenſions of <hi>Tycho</hi> and <hi>Lansberge</hi> are much contraverted, and I think not without cauſe; for it's certain, that the Circumradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy of the Planets glittering Beams, makes them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the eye, much bigger then they (truely) are, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appears by the Teleſcope, which you may experimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at pleaſure, by pricking a little hole in a peece of Pape<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or Paſtboord with the point of a Pin on Needle: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then through that narrow paſſage, if you obſerve the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66102:19"/> Planets and Stars on ſome clear nights, you will ſoon find how much they looſe of their borrowed luſtre.</p>
               <p>But I return, The Diſtances, Magnitudes and Colours of the ſeven Planets, according to the Dimenſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and built upon the acurate Obſervations of the Ancient and beſt Modern Aſtronomers, be as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Moon, when ſhe is furtheſt diſtant from the earth, is removed 4229 parts, and when neareſt the earth, is 3879. Her apparent Semidiamiter (when ſhe is Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaeon) is 15 min. 21 ſeconds, ſhe is 48 times leſſe then the earth, her colours and ſeveral ſhapes are ſo vulgarly known and obſerved, that I need not deſcribe them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Mercuries</hi> greateſt remotion from the earth, is 146764 parts, his neareſt diſtance is 53236 parts, his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Semidiamiter is 10 ſeconds, he (for I may call him either Maſculine or Feminine without any diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to his perſon) is 2800 times leſſe then the earth, by reaſon of the parvity of his Orbe: He is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſeen, and when he is, he appears a Star of duſky Silver colour.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Venus</hi> when ſhe is furtheſt from the earth, is diſtant 172937 parts, her leaſt diſtance is 27063. Her apparent Semidiamiter is 26 ſeconds and a half, ſhe is 157 times leſſe then the earth: ſhe appears a Star of a great and bright glory, inſomuch, that when ſhe is neareſt the earth, and furtheſt Elongate from the Sun, I have ſeen thouſands of men in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> (when they beheld her magnitude) admire her as ſome ſtrange Apparition or Blazing Star: So ignorant were they, that not one of a 1000 could deſcribe her. Oh profound ignorance in Coeleſtial Sciences!</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Sun</hi> when he is neareſt the earth (which is about the 19 of <hi>December</hi>) is diſtant from it 101798 parts, and when furtheſt from the earth (which is about the 17 day of <hi>June</hi>) is 98222. His apparent Semidiami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (when <hi>Aphelion</hi>) is 16 min. 28 ſeconds, he is 333 times greater then the earth, his colour is ſo wel known, that he that cannot ſee it, will not ſee to read it, though I ſhould deſcribe it.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:66102:20"/>5. <hi>Mars</hi> his greateſt diſtance from the earth, is 266435 parts, his leaſt diſtance 66435. His apparent Semidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter is 18 ſeconds, he is 150 times leſſe then the earth, and appears a Star of a fiery red, ſparkling, glowing colour.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Jupiter</hi> his great diſtance from the earth, is 644644. parts, his leaſt diſtance is 444644. His aparent Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diamiter is 25 ſeconds, he is leſſe then the earth once and a quarter, and appears a Star of a clear, bright, azure colour.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Saturn</hi> his greateſt diſtance from the earth, is 1108090 parts, his leaſt diſtance 908090. His appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Semidiamiter is 18 ſeconds and a half, and appears (to our ſight) a Star of a leaden, ſwarthy and pale colour.</p>
               <p>Being now arrived at the higheſt of all the Planets, I am now at a ſtand, to behold the vaſt and immenſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the fixed Stars: And while I am thinking upon it, there comes to my rememberance the words of our bleſſed Saviour, viz. <hi>In my Fathers houſe are many man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi> O Lord, it is moſt true; but if thou haſt created ſo many Millions of viſible Manſions, in theſe thy viſible, and (as to us) inferiour Spheres: What infinit Millions, millions, millions of inviſible Manſions is there in thoſe inviſible and ſuperiour Spheres, which are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thy glorious Angels, and they again comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thy Majeſty!</p>
               <p>Now, if (at any time) ye be deſirous to know the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of theſe ſeven Planets from the earth, in Miles, ſay by the Golden Rule, if 68 and a half give 3436 <hi>Italia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Scottiſh</hi> Miles: What ſhall the diſtance of the Plane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from the earth in parts give? Multiply and Divide, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Quotus</hi> will be your anſwer. But becauſe I woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have you to underſtand the Premiſes, I ſhall therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> add an Example or two for Illuſtration.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe it were required to know the diſtance of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moon from the Earth when ſhe is in her <hi>Aphelion,</hi> (o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greateſt remotion from the earth) her diſtance bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4229 parts. I ſay, if 68 and a half give 3436 miles, Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:66102:20"/> ſhall 4229 give? Multiply the ſecond Number by the third, the Product divide by the firſt, the Quotient is 212129. and ſo many Miles is the Moon diſtant from the earth when ſhe is in her <hi>Aphelion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall add another Example: The leaſt diſtance of the Sun from the Earth, is 98222. Now to know how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miles this is, I ſay, (as before) if 68 and half give 3436 Miles: What ſhall 98222 give? Multiply and Divide, and the <hi>Quotient</hi> is 4926872. and ſo many Miles is the Sun diſtant from the Earth when he is neareſt.</p>
               <p>In like manner, you may calculate the diſtances of the reſt of the Planets from the earth, either at their neareſt Vicinity or greateſt Remotion, according as I have ſhown you in theſe two Examples.</p>
               <p>If you would know the Diameters of the ſeven Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Orbs in Miles alſo, you muſt firſt know, that their particular Semidiamiters (in ſuch parts as aforeſaid) be as followeth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Saturn</hi> 952500.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mars</hi> 152040.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Venus</hi> 72405.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Moon</hi> 4047.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jupiter</hi> 519500.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sun</hi> 100000.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mercury</hi> 38240.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now, If you double the Planets Semidiameters, the Product is their Diameters, which multiplied by 22 and the Product divided by 7. the <hi>Quotient</hi> will ſhow you their particular Circumferences (in ſuch parts as their Diameters is) whick known, you may eaſily compute the Miles contained in the Circles of their ſeveral Orbs.</p>
               <p>As for Example, The Semidiamiter of the Moons Orb, is 4047. which doubled, is 8094 the Diameter, which multiplied by 22. the Product 178068 divided by 7. the <hi>Quotus</hi> 25438 is the parts contained in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of the Moons Orb.</p>
               <p>Now if you would know what Miles thoſe parts will give, ſay, if 68 and a half give 3436. What ſhall 25438 give? Multiplie and Divide, and the <hi>Quotient</hi> will be 1275984 for the Miles contained in the Circle of the Moons Orb. Thus having found the Circumference and Diameter of the Circle in Miles, you may eaſily find the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66102:21"/> Convex Superficies thereof, by multiplying the one by the other, the Product will be 518048228016 Miles, for the Superficies of the Moons Orb, a vaſt ſum indeed; yea, 'tis ſo much, that all the men and women that ever yet breathed, if they were aſſigned to dwell in the ſaids Orb, ſhould have more for their particular Manſions, then the limits of a Kingdom. O wonderful magnitude! But if there be ſuch regal manſions in the Mons Orb, which is but the leaſt and loweſt: What ſuper-infinit Manſions muſt there be in the reſt of the higher and greater Orbs of the other Planets? O what joy is it to contemplate the raviſhing Magnitudes and Motions of the Glorious Heavenly Hoſts of Almighty God!</p>
               <p>To the end that ye may better conceive the Order, Scituations and Various Diſtances of the ſeveral Coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Spheres, I ſhall here add the Type of the Syſtemn of the Viſible World, according to the Opinion and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, Ratified and Confirmed by the acurate Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of that Noble Daniſh Lord, <hi>Tycho Brahe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this annexed Figure, you may behold as in a Glaſs how excellently great JEHOVAH hath made the Frame and Machina of this Viſible World: What a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Oeconomy, Proportion and Coeleſtial Harmony is there to be ſeen and heard in this admired and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Fabrick! O man! ſet thy foot upon earth (it doth ſo by nature to teach thee not to ſet thy heart up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it) and lift up thine eyes, and behold the Glorious Hoſts of the moſt High and Almighty TETRAGRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MATON! and Adore with Admiration this Grand ARCHITAS, who hath made all his wondrous works in Number, Weight and Meaſure! O how admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably hath he made the Creation of the Univerſs, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate and inferiour one part to another. Heaven is a work on which he beſtoweth much coſt &amp; ſkill, to make a Throne for himſelf! The earth is a cheaper and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer peece of work, for a footſtool! Hell is his ſtrange work! A work, in which he enſtrangeth himſelf from himſelf! In which he goeth to the vaſteſt diſtance, to bring forth a work moſt unlike himſelf! In which he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66102:21"/> hides the workman in the horrour of the work, and ſhewes him by hiding him ſo deep! All things created are in their great Creator, Eminently, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.12. The night ſhineth, as the day; the darkneſſe, and the light are both alike to thee! Darkneſſe, and light, are both in GOD! Not only repreſentatively, but really! Not in their Ideas only, but their Indentities! Yet not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially, nor formally, but eminently! After a more perfect manner then they are in themſelves! As in the Supreme UNITY of all perfections!</p>
               <p>I have dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſed a little, but I ſhall preſently wheel into the Road again. The Type of the Mundane Syſtemn according to the opinion of <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> is as followeth.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of Tychonic system</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66102:22"/>
               <p>In this Figure, the uttermoſt Great Pricked Circle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents the Firmament (or eighth Sphere whein all the fixed Stars move) The Center whereof is the Earth. Here you ſee that all the Planets (except the Moon) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Sun for their common Node and Center. And that <hi>Saturn</hi> in oppoſition to the Sun, is nearer the earth then <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Apogeon.</hi> And that <hi>Mars</hi> in oppoſition, is nearer then the Sun himſelf. You may alſo perceive (in this Diagram) a Demonſtration of the Planets vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſtances from the earth. Why they are ſometimes more near to, and ſometimes more remot from the earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, of the diſtance of the fixed Stars from the earth, I can ſay nothing. For Obſervations tells us, that the Angle of Paralax (by which the diſtances of the Planets is exactly determined) is altogether inſenſible, as in relation of this Orb. And from thence it follows, that it is impoſſible (by the wit of man) to obtain either their Diſtances or Magnitudes;</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Trees, Herbs and Planets, under the government of the ſeven Planets.</head>
               <p>THe great wiſdom of a Phyſitian is to know what Planet cauſes the diſeaſe, and whether by Simpathy or Antipathy; for, as the cauſe is, ſo muſt the cure be, <hi>viz.</hi> Simpathetical, or Antipathetical: Simpathetical cures ſtrengthneth nature, Antipathetical cures in one degree or other weakneth it; But becauſe I am not now to act the part of a Phyſitian, (although I much honour their Functions) nor to preſcribe or medle with their Manual Operations; but as a <hi>Mathematician,</hi> I may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and acceptably direct my diſcourſe to the <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical</hi> Phyſitian, who of all others (in that Profeſſion) I eſteem moſt, for he only knows the Influence of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66102:22"/> Stars upon humane bodies, and can tell a mans diſeaſe by the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, without going to viſit the ſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to theſe Gentlemen therefore I direct my ſpeach. When a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eth a diſeaſe by Simpathy, the beſt and only way is to cure it by the Simpathetical Herbs under the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the ſaids Planet; but if he cauſe the diſeaſe by Antipathy, look to what Planet it's to, whether it be to the Sun or Moon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As for example, A young Student in Phyſick preſented an Urine to me, and deſired my Judgement what I thought of it, and of the Patient whoſe it was: I found <hi>Mars</hi> to be the cauſer of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and in partile oppoſition to <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſhe hard by the Dragons Tail, * I told him the Patient was afflicted in the Inſtruments of Generation, which was moſt true (as he confeſſed) Therefore I concluded that it was by Antipathy to <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſo I bade him make uſe of the Simpathetical Herbs of <hi>Venus</hi> for cure. I mention this Gentlemen, only for your beſt advantage in attaining the true cauſes of the diſeaſe, whether it be by the Nativity, Decumbiture, or Urine, that ſo you may ſpeedily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what Simpathetical Herbs are fit to cure it.</p>
               <p>But to return, the Herbs and Plants under the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Saturn,</hi> are, Barley, Redbeets, Byfoil, Birdsfoot, Biſtort, Buckhorn-plantane, Clavers, Comfray, Cudweed, Syatica-Creſſes, Croſwoort, Darnal, Dodar, Epithimum, Elm-tree, Fleawort, Flaxweed, Fumitory, Stinking-Gladwin, Gutwort, Hakweed, Humlock, Hemp, Henbane, Horſtail, Knapweed, Knotgraſſe, Medlartree, Moſs, Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Oſmond-royal, Nightſhade, Pylewort, Polipodium, Poplartree, Quinſtree, Rupturetree, Ruſhes, Solomons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeal, Saraſens-conſound, Servicetree, Splenwort, Tamari, Melancholy-thiſtle, Blackthorne, Throughwax, Tutſan, Woad.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herbs under <hi>Jupiter,</hi> be</head>
                  <p>Agrimony, Alexander, Aſparagus, Avens, Baytree, Whitebeets, Waterbetony, Woodbetony, Bilberries, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, Bugloſſe, Chervil, Sweetciſly, Cinqfoyl, Coſtmary, Dandeleon, (or rather Denſ-leonis, Lyonstooth,) Docks, Dogſgraſſe, Endivy, Hartſtongue, Hyſop, Houſleek, or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66102:23"/> Seengreen, Lungwort, Liverwoort, Sweetmaudlen, Oaktrees, Redroſes, Sage, Sawcealon, Scurvygraſſe, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, Ladies-thiſtles, Bloodwort.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herbs under <hi>Mars,</hi> be</head>
                  <p>Arſ-mart, Aſarabaca, Barberries, Sweetbazil, Bramble, Briony, Brooklime, Butcherſbroom, Broom, Broom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rape, Crowfoot, Cuckowpint, Cranbil, Cotton-thiſtle, Flaxweed, Furbuſh, Garleeks, Hathorn, Hops, Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Muſtard, Hedge-muſtard, Nadir, Netles, Onions, Pepperwort, Carduſbenedictus, Radiſh, Horſradiſh, Rubarb, Rapontick, Baſtard-Rubarb, Thiſtles, Starthiſtls, Woolythiſtle, Tobacco, Treacle, Muſtard, Mithridet-muſtard, Wold or Weld, Wormwood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herbs under the <hi>Sun,</hi> be</head>
                  <p>Angelica, Aſhtree, Balm, Oneblade, Burnet, Butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bur, Cammomill, Celandine, Centaury, Ibright, Saint-Johns wort, Loveage, Marigolds, Miſleto, Peony, Saint Peters wort, Pimpernel, Roſaſolis, Roſemary, Rue, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, Tormentil, Turnſole, Viperſbugloſſe, Walnut-tree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herbs under <hi>Venus,</hi> be</head>
                  <p>Alhoofe, Aldertree, Apletree, Arach wyld and ſtinking Archangel, Beans, Ladiesbedſtrow, Birchtree, Biſhops<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weed, Blits, Bugle, Bardock, Chery tree Chickweed, Cich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe, Clary, Cockshead, Coltsfoot, Cowſlips, Daiſies, Devilsbit, Elder, Eringo, Fetherfew, Figwort, Filipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula, Foxgloves, Goldenrod, Gromwel, Groundſel, Herb-Robert, Herbtrew-love, Kidneyswort, Ladiesmantle, Malows, Mint, Motherwort, Mugwort, Neips, Parſneips, Peachtree, Peartree, Penyroyal, Periwinkle, Plantan, Plumbtree, Primroſes, Ragwort, Sorel, Sowthiſtles, Spig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, Strawberies, garden-Tanſie, wyld-Tanſie, Tezles, Vervain, Vinetree, Violets, Wheat, Yarow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herbs under <hi>Mercury,</hi> be</head>
                  <p>Calamint, Carats, Caroways, Dill, Elecompane, Fenel, Fern, Germander, Haſlenut-tree, Horehound, Hounds-tongue, Lavender, Liquoris, Walrue, Maidenhair, ſweet Marjorum, Melilot, Moneywort, Mulberytree, Oats, Perſly, Cowparſnip, Pelitory, of the wall, Groundpine, Reſtha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Samphire, Winter and Summer Savory, Scabions,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66102:23"/> Smalage, Southernwood, Meadowtreefoyl, Gardenvale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, Woodbin, or Honyſuckles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Herbs under the <hi>Moon</hi> be,</head>
                  <p>Aderſtongue, Cabages, Coleworts, Columbines, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercreſſes, Duckweed, Waterflag, Flowerdeluce, Fluelin, Ivy, Letice, Waterlillies, Loſeſtriſe, Moonwort, Monſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ear, Orpine, Popyes, Purſlain, Privet, Ratlegraſſe, White-roſes, White-ſaxifrage, Winter-Gilitflowers, the Willowtree.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the particular Diſeaſes which the Planets ſignifie.</head>
               <p>HAving told you in the preceeding Chapter of the particular Herbs and Planets under the government of the ſeven Planets, my next Talk is, to ſhow what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes each particular Planet ſignifieth, and they are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> cauſeth Toothach, Quartan agues, all diſeaſes of Melancholy, Cold and Dryneſſe, Leproſie, Rhumes, Conſumptions, Black-jaundice, Palſies, Tremblings, Vain fears, Gouts, Hemarhoids, Broken bones, Diſlocations, Deafneſſe, Ruptures, (if <hi>Saturn</hi> be in <hi>Leo</hi> or <hi>Scorpio</hi>) Iliack paſſion, Chin-couch, Pains in the Blader, all long Diſeaſes, all madneſs that comes of Melancholy or Fears of a Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goblin, or Brouny.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> all infirmities of the Liver and Veins, Infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Lungs, Plurifies and other Apoſthums about the Breaſt and Ribs, all diſeaſes proceeding of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction of Blood, Wind, Quinſies and Feavers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> Peſtilences, Burning-Feavers, Tertian and Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian agues, Megrim, Carbuncles and Plague ſores, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, Scadings, Ringworms, Bliſters, Phrenſies, Fury, Hairbrains, Sudden diſtempers of the Head coming of heat, Yellow-jaundice, Bloody-flux, Fiſtulas, all wounds
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66102:24"/> whatſoever, Diſeaſes in the Inſtruments of Generation, Stones in the Reins or Bladder, Scars and Pockholls in the Face, all hurts by Iron or Fire, all diſeaſes coming of Choler, Anger or Paſſion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sun</hi> cauſeth Pimples and Buries in the Face, Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Heart, Heart-burning, Trembling, Faintings, Sore eyes, Diſeaſes of the Mouth, all diſeaſes of the heart, Stinking breath, Rotten feavers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus,</hi> all diſeaſes of the Womb, as Suffocation, Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation, Diſlocations, all diſeaſes incident to the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Generation, the Reins and Navel, running of the Reins, <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> Priapiſmus, all diſeaſes coming by inordinate Love or Luſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> all diſeaſes of the Brain, as Vertigos, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, diſeaſes of the Lungs, as Aſthme, Phthiſicks, all imperfections of the Tongue, as Stammering, Liſping and Hoarſneſſe, Coughs, Snuffling in the Noſe, Stoping of the Head, Dumbneſſe, Folly and Simplicity (the Epede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical diſeaſes of the Time) and whatſoever hurts the Intellectual Faculty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall live <hi>Mercury,</hi> and come a little lower to the <hi>Moon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Moon cauſes, the Cholick, Belly-ach, ſtoping and overflowing the Terms in Women, all cold and Rhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Diſeaſes, Worms in the Belly, hurts in the Eyes, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits, rotten Coughs, Convulſions, Falling-ſickneſſes, the Kings-evil, Smal-pox, and Meaſles, all Coagulate and crude humors in any part of the body, Lethargy and Flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Diſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Shewing how to rectifie a Nativity by the trutine of herms.</head>
               <p>THe firſt and eaſieſt way of rectifying an Nativity, and reducing it to that moment of time when the Infant made its exit from the dark priſon of the Mothers womb,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66102:24"/> and began to be a viſible member of the Creation, is by the trutine or ſcrutiny of <hi>herms</hi> (one of the wiſeſt of all mortall men, and as ancient as <hi>Moſes</hi>) who was of this opinion, that the very degree of the ſame ſign wherein the <hi>Moon</hi> was at the Conception of the Childe, ſhould be the true ſign and degree of the aſcendant at the Birth; this way of Rectification is far more ancient then the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mador of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and allowed by <hi>Ptolomy</hi> himſelf, in his 51 <hi>Centiloquium,</hi> his words are, <hi>What ſign the Moon is in at the time of the Birth, make that very ſign the aſcendant at Conception, and what ſigns the Moon is in at Conception, make that ſame ſign, or the oppoſite unto it, the ſign aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the Birth,</hi> &amp;c. He therefore that would know the exact time aforeſaid (its no matter whither it relate to himſelf or another,) muſt firſt erect a Coeleſtial Scheme for the eſtimate time of the Birth, and rectifie the place of the Moon thereto, and place her in the Figure.</p>
               <p>Then take the diſtance of the Moon from the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, if ſhe be Subteranean, (or under the earth) and from the ſeventh houſe if ſhe be above the earth, ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the ſigns and degrees of the Angles, from the ſigns and degrees of the Moon (by adding 12 ſigns if Subſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction cannot otherwiſe be made) and with the diſtance of the Moon from the Angle, enter the Table, Intituled, <hi>A Table of the manſion of the Childe in his Mothers womb.</hi> Under the titles of ſigns and degrees, ſeeking the neareſt Number thereunto, and over againſt that, under the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns of the Moon, under, or above the earth, and in the reſpective Columns, you will find the certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of dayes, that the Childe remained in the dark priſon of its Mothers womb.</p>
               <p>This done, conſider whither the year of Birth be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or Biſextile, and what day of the year the Birth is, then Subſtract the number of dayes that the Childe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the womb, from the day of the birth, (by adding 365 or 366 (according as the year of birth is common or Biſextile) if Subſtraction cannot otherwiſe be made) and with the reſidue enter the Table of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, under the year of Birth, and you will find the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66102:25"/> and day of the Month, when the Childe was Conceived.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A Table of the Manſion of the Childe in its Mothers Womb.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2">Signs. Degr. </cell>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2">
                           <hi>Luna ſub terra.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2">
                           <hi>Luna ſupra terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="3">A Table of the Moneths.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Moneths</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Common years.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Biſext. years.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>0 0</cell>
                        <cell>273</cell>
                        <cell>258</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>January</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>0 12</cell>
                        <cell>274</cell>
                        <cell>259</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>February</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>59</cell>
                        <cell>60</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>0 24</cell>
                        <cell>275</cell>
                        <cell>260</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>March</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>91</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 6</cell>
                        <cell>276</cell>
                        <cell>261</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>April</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>121</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1 18</cell>
                        <cell>277</cell>
                        <cell>262</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>May</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>151</cell>
                        <cell>152</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 0</cell>
                        <cell>278</cell>
                        <cell>263</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>June</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>181</cell>
                        <cell>182</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 12</cell>
                        <cell>279</cell>
                        <cell>264</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>July</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>212</cell>
                        <cell>213</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2 24</cell>
                        <cell>280</cell>
                        <cell>265</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Auguſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>243</cell>
                        <cell>244</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 6</cell>
                        <cell>281</cell>
                        <cell>266</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Septemb.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>273</cell>
                        <cell>274</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 18</cell>
                        <cell>282</cell>
                        <cell>267</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>October</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>304</cell>
                        <cell>305</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 0</cell>
                        <cell>283</cell>
                        <cell>268</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Novemb.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>334</cell>
                        <cell>335</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 12</cell>
                        <cell>284</cell>
                        <cell>269</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>365</cell>
                        <cell>366</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4 24</cell>
                        <cell>285</cell>
                        <cell>270</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5 6</cell>
                        <cell>286</cell>
                        <cell>271</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>dayes</cell>
                        <cell>dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5 18</cell>
                        <cell>287</cell>
                        <cell>272</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6 0</cell>
                        <cell>288</cell>
                        <cell>273</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Then obſerve the place of the Moon, the day of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception at noon, which if ſhe be not diſtant from the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate angle (or aſcendant of the Nativity) above 13 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, then the day found is the day of Conception, but if ſhe is more remote, you may imagine either the good aſpects of the Fortuns put the Birth forwards, or the untoward aſpects of the infortuns retarded it.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I come next to practice, and for illuſtration thereof, I ſhall adde one Example with as much brevity as I can.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:66102:25"/>
               <p>A Childe was born in the famous City of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> Anno Chriſti, 1632. upon Sunday the 15 of <hi>July,</hi> about half an hour paſt 8 in the morning, as was obſerved and is reported.</p>
               <p>At which eſtimate time aforeſaid, the Cuſp of the aſcendant is <hi>Virgo,</hi> 18. deg. 19 min. (in the Latitude of 56. degrees) The Moon is <hi>ſub terra</hi> under the Earth) viz. within the limits of the third Houſe in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> 10 degrees 25. min. Now to know the Month and day when the Childe was conceived, I marſhal the matter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the following method.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Sig.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">deg.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>True place of the Moon</cell>
                        <cell>7.</cell>
                        <cell>10.</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Cuſpe of the aſcendant <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> Subſtract.</cell>
                        <cell>5.</cell>
                        <cell>18.</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſts the diſtance Moon from the aſcendant.</cell>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>22.</cell>
                        <cell>06</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>With which diſtance, I enter the Table of the Childes Manſion, and the neareſt number thereto in ſigns and degrees, is 1 ſign, 18 degrees. Againſt which (in the Column, Intituled, <hi>Sub terra,</hi> or the Moon under the Earth) I find 277. intimating that the native was 277 dayes in the obſcure priſon of his mothers womb.</p>
               <p>The native was born in 1632. which divided by four, and nothing remaining, ſhewes 'tis a Biſextile year.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">dayes,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Number of the dayes from <hi>January</hi> 1 to the 15 of <hi>July</hi> in a Biſextile year, is,</cell>
                        <cell>197</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>For facility of operation I add the number of dayes in a Biſextile year,</cell>
                        <cell>366</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Aggregate</cell>
                        <cell>563</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>From which I ſubſtract the number of dayes that the Childe was in his Mothers womb,</cell>
                        <cell>277</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſts</cell>
                        <cell>286</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Which in the Table of Moneths (for the Biſextile year) points out the 12 of <hi>October</hi> 1631. on which day
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66102:26"/> the Childe was conceived. The Moon that day at noon (according to preciſe Calculation from <hi>Keplers</hi> Tables) was in <hi>Virgo,</hi> 20 deg. 56 min. 31 ſeconds, which is not above 3 degrees diſtant from the aſcendant at birth: And therefore I conclude that the Childe was conceived the 12 of <hi>October</hi> 1631. as aforeſaid. And thus much ſhall ſerve, for the Correction of a Nativity by the <hi>Trutina Hermetis.</hi> There be other wayes of Rectifying the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate time aforeſaid, as the Animodar of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and accidents of the Native, which Latter is moſt exact, and that which I make practice of next, the Trutine of Herms.</p>
               <p>If you deſire to know, whither the Childe be likely to live any ſpace after it's born; for many times we ſee Children live but a few Months; yea, ſome but a few dayes, hours, or minuts: Sometimes the Mothers womb becomes the Infants Tomb. O how thankful to God ſhould we be, who are preſerved to the age of 30. 40. 50, &amp;c. 'Tis a great bleſſing from God to have a long leaſe of our life, whoſe kindneſſe and infinit love we ſhould endeavour to requite, by ſpending it in Divine Contemplations and Adorations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, if you would know (from the Hierogliphical Characters of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,) whither the Infant will live paſt his Infancy, then obſerve theſe few Aphoriſms following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Erect a Coeleſtial Schem upon the eſtimative time given, and correct the ſame by the Trutine of Herms as aforeſaid, and then obſerve.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If there be an unfortunate Planet in the Aſcendant vitiating the degree thereof, or in <hi>Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> unto it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> be conjoyned in the Aſcendant, or if the light of the time be afflicted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Lord of the Aſcendant Combuſt, Cadent, or Retrograde.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If all the Planets be Subteranean, or if the Birth be upon a new or full Moon.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Moon in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> or <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 4th, 6th, 8th or 12th Houſes.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66102:26"/>7. The Moon beſieged between the bodies of <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> void of all helps from the Fortunes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The light of the time eclipſed at the moment of birth, is a ſure argument of a ſhort life.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If the birth be by day (<hi>viz.</hi> between the Suns riſing and his ſeting) then have ſpecial regard to the Sun; if by night, to the Moon, becauſe he is, <hi>Fons vitalis Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, Luna naturalis,</hi> according to <hi>Ptolomy, Cent. Aphoriſ.</hi> 86. and according to the firſt Aphoriſm of <hi>Herms Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſtus, (Sol &amp; Luna poſt Deum, omnium viventium vita ſunt)</hi> they are the life of all living creatures. And therefore if the Luminaries be ſtrong or well dignified, or in a good Houſe of Heaven, or in a favourable Aſpect of <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> whither the native be born by day, or by night, 'tis a ſure argument that the childe then born may live long, but if otherwiſe, they deny long life.</p>
               <p n="10">10. They who are born upon a full Moon, dye by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, or too great abundance of moiſture; and upon a new Moon, for want of humidity, or by reaſon of too much dryneſſe; uſually the moſt ſickly, ſmall and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bodies, are brought forth upon the change of the Moon.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Conjunction of many Planets in the Aſcendant void of all Eſſential Dignities, argueth a ſhort life <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. The Lord of the Aſcendant going to the Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Lord of the 8. or if the Lord of the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant be in the 8. or Lord of the 8. in the Aſcendant, the ſame.</p>
               <p n="13">13. If the Luminaries ſeparate from a fortune, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to a Malevolent, the Childe ſhall then be in great danger of death, at what time that Luminary (by a juſt meaſure of time) comes either to the body, or hath a courſe to that unhappy Aſpect.</p>
               <p n="14">14. If you ſhould happen to perceive ſuch an applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as aforeſaid, and would know the time when the eminent danger will happen, take and reſolve the Ark of Direction into Time, by allowing to every degree one
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66102:27"/> year, five dayes, eight hours, and ſo you will be eaſily enformed of the time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the general teſtimonies of a ſhort life, if none of them happen in a nativity, the childe may live until ſome eminent direction of the Sun, Moon or Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, unto ſome Malevolent Promittor, prove the cruel <hi>Atropos</hi> to cut in two the threed of life.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fac ut experiar, JEHOVA, finem meum, menſura dierum, quid ſit; experiar quam durabilis ſum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Of the Year what it is, and the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity thereof.</head>
               <p>A Year is the moſt principal, ordinary, common and uſual part of time, whereby not only the ages of men and other accidents of the world are meaſured, but alſo the times of (almoſt) all our actions in the world, their beginnings, progreſſe, durations and intervals, are ſquared and reckoned thereby: and albeit the ſaids ſpace of time, called (years) are variouſly accounted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cuſtome of diverſe Nations, greater in ſome, and leſſer in others; yet hath it (or at leaſt wiſe ſhould have) its principal dependance upon the true place and motion of the Sun, by which the years are meaſured, and therefore they are rightly divided into Aſtronomical and Political.</p>
               <p>The Aſtronomical years are meaſured, either according to the Periodical motion of the Sun, or the Conjunction of the Moon with the Sun, and therefore twofold, <hi>viz. Solar</hi> or <hi>Lunar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Solar</hi> year is that ſpace of time, that the Sun (by his proper motion) is departing from ſome Radical or fixed Point of the Ecliptique, to his return to the ſame again, and this may be called either Tropical or Syderial.</p>
               <p>The Tropical year, is that ſpace of time in which the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66102:27"/> Sun is departing from one of the Tropical, Equinoctial, or Solſtitial Points, and (running through the whole Ecliptique) returns to the ſame Point again. The true length of this year (according to the acurate Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Ancient and Modern Aſtronomers) is 365 dayes, 5 hours, 49 min. 4 ſec.</p>
               <p>The Syderal (or Starry year) is that ſpace of time, wherein the Sun is departing from ſome fixed Star, or determined Point of the 8 Sphere, and returns to the ſame again: the true Quantity whereof (immutably) is 365 dayes, 6 hours, 9 min. 21 ſeconds.</p>
               <p>The Political or Civil years be ſuch as are every where uſed for diſtinction of times, wherein a reſpect is had to the motions of the Luminaries, Conjunctly or Severally.</p>
               <p>The year is uſually called either Common or Biſextile, the common year contains (according to the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi>) 365 dayes, 6 hours, which 6 hours make every fourth year Leap-year, which contains 366 dayes: it is called Biſextile of <hi>Bis</hi> and <hi>Sex</hi> (twice ſix) becauſe the ſixth Calends of <hi>March</hi> is twice repeated: it is called <hi>Intercalar,</hi> becauſe of the day that is put in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween and Leap-year, becauſe that (by the addition of a day) the fixed holy dayes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do, as it were, leap one day further into the week, then it was in the year pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the Judgement of the Weather from the Coeleſtial Bodies.</head>
               <p>ALthough the knowledge of the Weather be a thing ſo common, yet the true Key is exceeding diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult: and therefore I have thought it neceſſary to write ſomething thereof, that the world may ſee and know that our Judgement of the Weather in our yearly Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacks is not built upon a meer conjecture or bare gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66102:28"/> (as Millions of ignorant men think) but upon prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of reaſon, and that reaſon ratified and confirmed by many hundreds (if not thouſands) of years experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and yet it's but counted (amongſt ignorant Aſſes) at beſt, but gueſſings: I charge my Readers for the future, that they do not carp at that (in my Book) which they cannot imitate, leſt they attain to the honour of being branded for Ignorant Fools, whoſe dimmer eyes are not able to penetrate the Aſtral Spheres, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dave digreſſed a little, but I ſhall preſently wheel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Road again, and perform what I have promiſed, with as much brevity and facility as I can.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To the time of the Suns ingreſſe into <hi>Aries,</hi> and to the Conjunctions or Oppoſitions of the Luminaries pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the ſame. Erect Coeleſtial Schems, then ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve whether the place of the Luminaries at the time of their <hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> (preceeding the Ingreſſe) happened in a moyſt, cold or dry Manſions, and of what Planets they are aſpected.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhall be well diſpoſed in an Angle, and in a moiſt Aſteriſm, without impediment, neither applying to another Planet at the time of the Suns Ingreſſe, it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſageth temperate and ſeaſonable ſhowres, and fills the Heavens with obſcure Clouds; but eſpecially in that Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation wherein he hath the chief dominion. — Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if <hi>Saturn</hi> be impedite or evil diſpoſed, it portends turbu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent Storms of Wind and Rain, &amp; cold denſe thick clouds eſpecially if <hi>Mercury</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall be in moiſt ſigns, and behold him from an Angle, for in ſuch a caſe the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger may predict of much Rain.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſhall be in ſuch a Poſition, it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Winds and Rain, with rediſh Clouds.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Mars</hi> ſo poſited, ſignifies yellow Clouds, Thunder Coruſcations and Rain, eſpecially in thoſe times prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and convenient, and the rather if <hi>Jupiter</hi> or <hi>Mercuriu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> give any teſtimony thereof.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Sun in ſuch a Poſition, as aforeſaid ſhewet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Red Clouds, and great ſtore of Wet: There are ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the beſt Aſtologers who wil not Elect the Sun and Moo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:66102:28"/> for Rulers, becauſe they are general ſignificators of the Times.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Moon applying to <hi>Venus,</hi> and aſſuming the prerogatives aforeſaid, bringeth gentle Rain, or at leaſt wiſe Clouds, but if the Moon ſhall apply to <hi>Mercury,</hi> or if <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhall be Lord and Ruler of the Figure with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> it portends Showres and violent Winds, and a cloudy Air, yet ſomewhat more violent, and ſometime again more remiſs in reſpect of ſigns, manſions of the Moon, and eratick Stars.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If the Panet ruling ſhall be Oriental, his effects will appear in the end of time, if Occidental, in the beginning whither it be in a Revolution or Solar Ingreſſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Many Planets, eſpecially <hi>Saturn, Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> in Northern Signs, argue a hot Summer, and a Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Winter. The contrary when many Planets (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the three aforeſaid) are in Southern Signs, for ſo they ſignifie a cold and moiſt Periſtaſis of the Air, and a colder Winter.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Saturn</hi> in Southern Signs, and eſpecially in <hi>Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn</hi> or <hi>Aquary,</hi> argue terrible Winters of Froſt and Cold, Summers remiſs in heat.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In the Revolution of the year, if <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall be in <hi>Aries</hi> or <hi>Scorpio,</hi> it portends much Rain: if in the houſes of <hi>Saturn,</hi> it ſheweth but little, in others a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity.</p>
               <p n="11">11. In the <hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> preceeding the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of the year, if <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall behold the ſame place, it ſignifies Lightning and Thunder, and ſometimes a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met hath ſucceeded ſuch a Poſition.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In the Revolution of the year, when <hi>Venus, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> are found in moiſt Manſions, it por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends much Rain.</p>
               <p n="13">13. At the Ingreſſe of the Sun into the Tropick ſigns, if <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall aſpect the Moon from a moiſt place, it's a ſign of much Rain: or if <hi>Mars</hi> from <hi>Scorpio</hi> ſhall aſpect <hi>Venus,</hi> it pretends likewiſe Rain.</p>
               <p n="14">14. When the Sun is in <hi>Aries</hi> or <hi>Taurus,</hi> if <hi>Venus</hi> be then Retrograde, the Spring will be moiſt.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:66102:29"/>15. Upon a <hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of the three ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Planets, either mutually, or with the three inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours: if the Moon ſoon after apply unto them by a <hi>Quartile</hi> or oppoſite Aſpect, then be ſure of Rain or Winds, according to the nature of theſe Planets ſo Aſpected.</p>
               <p n="16">16. When the <hi>Moon</hi> or any other Planet, tranſits the Angles of the Worlds Revolution, or Angles of the new and full Moon, then look for ſome change of Air, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the nature of thoſe Planets and Angles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> How to Prognoſticate more particularly of the Weather by the Planets mutual Aſpects.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe <hi>Conjunction</hi> of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> is a rare Aſpect, happening but once in twelve years, and therefore ought acurately to be obſerved; for it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth its effects in the mutations of the Air, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes before and after, becauſe of the Tardity of their motions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If this <hi>Conjunction</hi> happen in hot and dry manſions, it will produce dryneſſe accordingly; it increaſeth heat in Summer, and mitigats the cold in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but if it happen in moiſt ſigns, it portends Rain and Inundations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If <hi>Saturn</hi> claim principal dominion in the place of the <hi>Conjunction,</hi> it ſignifieth many diſeaſes, and much evil in general; but if <hi>Jupiter</hi> prevail (as he doth in the year 1663. the <hi>Conjunction</hi> happening in <hi>Sagitary</hi>) it's a ſign that much good ſhall follow within few years, and that many unneceſſary Cuſtoms ſhall be aboliſhed, and many wholeſome Laws eſtabliſhed, ere the effects of that <hi>Conjunction</hi> ſhall determine.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe ponderous Planets in <hi>Oppoſition, Quartile, Trine,</hi> or <hi>Sextile,</hi> is a ſign of continuance of ſeaſons; but for the moſt part, they bring forth temperate ſtorms of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66102:29"/> Rain and Hail, particularly happening in the Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time: in moiſt Aſteriſms, it produceth turbulent Air, in Summer Thunder, in Autumn Winds and Wet, in Winter thick Clouds and dark Air.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> produceth Winds, Hail, Lightning, Thunder and Coruſcations, according to the ſeaſons of the year: In the Spring, Wind, Rain and Thunder: In Summer, Hail and Thunder: In Autumn, violent Rain: And in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, diminution of cold.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Sol</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> is, <hi>Apertio portarum,</hi> if it happens in moiſt conſtellations. In Spring it threatens cold Clouds: in Summer, Hail, Thunder and remiſſion of Heat: in Autumn, Cold and Rain: in Winter, Froſt, Snow and cold weather.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> generally produceth cold Rain and Showres. In Spring, Rain: in Summer, ſudden and haſty ſhowres: in Autumn, cold Rain: in Winter ſnow.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> In the Spring produceth Winds and Rain, in Summer, winds and ſhowres: in Autumn, winds and clouds: in Winter cold and ſnow.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Saturn</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> in moiſt ſigns, portends clouds and coldneſſe, in Airy ſigns, cold, eſpecially in dry ſigns, ſharp air, and (if it be Winter) a froſty ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> changeth the quality of the air, according to the quality of the Signs and Stars, which they are joyned with or aſpected to. If in hot and dry manſions it cauſeth great heat, in moiſt ſigns thunder and rain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Jupiter</hi> and the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> brings forth blaſts of wholeſome winds and ſerenity, particularly in Spring, and in Autumn winds, in Summer thunder, in Winter remiſſion of cold.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> doth generally produce ſerenity, and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of air: in moiſt ſigns it promiſeth gentle ſhowres,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66102:30"/> in other ſigns fair weather, wholeſome winds, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of all things.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercurius,</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> ſtirreth up winds and rain in fiery ſigns, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets dryneſſe and warm winds in airy fair weather, but winds at all times in the year when they are in ſuch mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Aſpects.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Jupiter</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> alters the quality of the air according to the ſigns they poſſeſſe, but generally a temperate ſeaſon.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Mars</hi> and the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> in fiery ſigns portends heat and dryneſſe: In the watry, hail, thunders and lightning, in the airy clouds, and in the earthly, violent winds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> in or from moyſt ſigns, argueth abundance of (if not too much) rain eſpecially in Spring and Autumn: In Summer ſhowres, in Winter remiſſion of cold, and ſnow if <hi>Saturn</hi> behold them.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Mercurius</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition:</hi> in Winter and Spring argueth ſnow, in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hail and thunder, in Autumn great winds, in fiery and dry ſigns, exceſſive drowth and winds.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Mars</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> in moiſt ſigns rain, in fiery, dryneſſe, red clouds, and ſometimes rain, in Summer hail, lightning and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſcations.</p>
               <p n="18">18. The <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in <hi>Conjunction,</hi> commonly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth moiſture, in Spring and Autumn rain, in Summer ſhowres and thunder.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Conjunction,</hi> in the airy ſigns produce winds, in the watry rains, in the fiery warm winds.</p>
               <p n="20">20. The <hi>Sun</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> in <hi>Conjunction, Quartile</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> in moiſt ſigns portends rain, in fiery, fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but generally it alters the air, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſeaſon and ruling Planet.</p>
               <p n="21">21. When the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhall enter the 18 degree of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> if <hi>Venus</hi> be (then) in a moiſt place, it's a ſign of rain.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66102:30"/>22. In Winter, if <hi>Venus</hi> be direct and Oriental, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies but little rain at the beginning, but more at the end.</p>
               <p n="23">23. When <hi>Venus</hi> applieth to <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Scorpio,</hi> it brings rain immediatly.</p>
               <p n="24">24. When the <hi>Sun</hi> and the <hi>Moon, Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhall be all conjoyned together, it argueth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſhowres that day.</p>
               <p n="25">25. At the time of the <hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of the Luminaries, if <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall be in an Angle, it's a certain ſign of rain.</p>
               <p n="26">26. The Lord of the Aſcendant in (<hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of the Luminaries) a moiſt ſign produceth rain.</p>
               <p n="27">27. When the <hi>Moon</hi> ſhall come to the ſign aſcending of her <hi>Quartile, Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> the time ſhall be changed according to the quality and nature of the ſign and Aſteriſm.</p>
               <p n="28">28. A ſpecial regard muſt be had to the nature of the earth and air you live in (or write for) I mean, peculiar to your Horizon; becauſe that in all places they are not of alike nature, neither do the winds blow alike in all Horizons, ſome being Tropical and peculiar to one place, others Chronical, which come at a certain time of the year, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Vulgar Obſervations of the changes of the Weather.</head>
               <p>IN the preceeding Chapters, I have given you the choiceſt Aphoriſms, for giving judgement upon the weather: and I am confident, that he which underſtands them (which I fear will not be many) may not only give a probable conjecture of the weather, for (one) but many years to come; But becauſe the preceeding Aphoriſms may happen to (ſome) to be of difficult underſtanding to the illiterate, I ſhall therefore ſhew (even the moſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66102:31"/> rural) how to foretell the changes of the weather, if he have but the eyes of ſenſe and underſtanding in his head: and for his greater facility, I ſhall Marſhal the method in theſe ſeven Deviſions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Signs of fair weather.</item>
                  <item>2. Signs of rain.</item>
                  <item>3. Signs of wind.</item>
                  <item>4. Signs of hot weather.</item>
                  <item>5. Signs of drought.</item>
                  <item>6. Signs of cold weather.</item>
                  <item>7. Sings of froſts continuance.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This is the method, now to the matter.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>1. Signs of fair weather.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Sun riſing and ſetting clear: 2. The Moon clear three dayes after the Change, or before the Full: 3. Spots appearing in a Full Moon: 4. Clouds with golden edges towards Sun ſetting: 5. A cloudy ſky clearing againſt the wind: 6. The Rain bow appearing only Red and Yellow: 7. A Red Evening or a Gray Morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>2. Signs of rain.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. When the Sun in his riſing is hidden with a black cloud: 2. When the Moon (within three or four days after the Change) is blunt on both horns: 3. The Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow appearing in a fair day, the greener, the more rain: 4. The extraordinary chattering of the Pyets: 5. Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell licking their hoofs behind: 6. When the greateſt Stars only appear, and that miſty: 7. Lute or Viol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrings breaking untouched.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>3. Signs of wind.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Red clouds in a morning. 2. Often ſhooting of Stars: 3. Clouds flying ſwiftly in a clear air: 4. The Rain-bow red: 5. Black circles with red ſtrakes about the Sun or Moon: 6. Stars dimn and fiery, it's a ſign of winde and ſhowres when the Sun beams appear before he riſeth: 7. If the Sun ſets pale, or be encloſed with a black circle when he is near the time of his ſetting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:66102:31"/>
                  <head>4. Signs of hot weather.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Many Bats flying abroad ſooner then ordinary: 2. A white miſt riſing out of Moores and Waters before the Sun riſe: 3. The Kyts (or Gleds) flying high in the air: 4. Crowes or Ravens gaping againſt the Sun: 5. Great ſtore of Flyes and Midges playing in the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine towards night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>5. Signs of drought.</head>
                  <p>Stars ſeeming dimn or fiery red, ſignifies both drought and wind.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Signs of cold weather,</head>
                  <p>As froſt, ſnow or hail. 1. Clouds flying low, ſeeming to touch the tops of hills: 2. Great flocks of ſmall Birds gathered together: 3. If in the Winter the Sun ſhine clear towards night: 4. The extraordinary twinkling of the Stars: 5. Clouds upon heaps like Rocks: 6. An obſcure circle about the Sun or Moon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>7. Signs of froſts continuance.</head>
                  <p>Snow falling ſmall in the beginning of a froſt; but if the ſnow fall bigg, <hi>viz.</hi> in great flakes, then it's like to thaw very ſuddenly, eſpecially if the Southwind blow.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of the Winds, their Names and Natures.</head>
               <p>DAyly experience ſheweth that the diſpoſition of the Air is much varied by the Scituation of Winds, for according to their different bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing is the Seaſon much inclined, ſometime to Wind, Rain, and Snow, and ſometime to fair weather.</p>
               <p>The wind (it ſelf) is nothing elſe but an exhalation or earthly humor paſſing over the Superficies of the Earth; or it is an Eliſian, or drawing forth of the Air out of a cold Region.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:66102:32"/>
               <p>The four principal or Cardinal Winds which comes from the four Angles of the World, are called, the Eaſt, Weſt, North and South, the <hi>Latins</hi> calls them <hi>Septentrio, Auſter, Favonius,</hi> and <hi>Subſolanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Septentrio,</hi> the North wind, is cold and dry, is very wholſome, bringing ſerenity, preſervating all things from corruption, albeit it be hurtful and pernicious to Flowers, young and tender Plants, by reaſon of its exceſſive coldneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auſter,</hi> the South wind, is warm and moiſt, ſultry, hurtfull and dangerous, hurts the ſight, ſtuffes the head, makes men ſlothfull, engenders Diſeaſes, putrid Feavers, Pluriſies, Inflamations of the Lungs, and when this wind produceth ſerenity, it's with great heat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Favonius,</hi> the Weſt wind, (called <hi>Zephyrus</hi>) is moiſt and watry, begetting Rain and Thunder, but in Summer fair weather, in Winter and Spring, Snow or Rain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Subſolanus eurus,</hi> the Eaſt wind, is temperatly dry, it produceth Rhumes and cold Dewes, it bloweth moſt commonly at the Suns riſing, and (for the moſt part) little in the night time.</p>
               <p>Theſe four are called <hi>Venti principalles,</hi> the chief winds, the intermediate winds between theſe, be North-eaſt, South-eaſt, South-weſt, North-weſt.</p>
               <p>The North-eaſt wind is (for the moſt part) cold and dry, ingendring clouds, and ſomtimes Snow; The South-eaſt wind, is weak, moiſt, and producer of clouds and obſcure air: The South-weſt wind is of a hurtfull qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſickly, moiſt, producing clouds and rain: The North-weſt wind is moſt tonitruous, tempeſtuous, violent and haſty, cauſing a turbulent air.</p>
               <p>The Laterall winds, are in number eight, viz. Eaſt, north-eaſt, North north-eaſt, North north-weſt, Weſt, ſouth-weſt, South ſouth-weſt, South ſouth-eaſt, Weſt north-weſt, Eaſt ſouth-eaſt.</p>
               <p>The Colaterall winds are in number ſixteen, viz.
<list>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66102:32"/>
                     <item>1. Eaſt by North.</item>
                     <item>2. North-eaſt by Eaſt.</item>
                     <item>3. North by Eaſt.</item>
                     <item>4. Northeaſt by North.</item>
                     <item>5. North by Weſt.</item>
                     <item>6. Northweſt by North.</item>
                     <item>7. Weſt by North.</item>
                     <item>8. Northweſt by Weſt.</item>
                     <item>9. Southweſt by Weſt.</item>
                     <item>10. Weſt by South.</item>
                     <item>11. Southweſt by South.</item>
                     <item>12. South by Weſt.</item>
                     <item>13. South by Eaſt.</item>
                     <item>14. Southeaſt by South.</item>
                     <item>15. Southeaſt by Eaſt.</item>
                     <item>16. Eaſt by South.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having demonſtrated briefly the Names and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Winds, I ſhall in the next Chapter ſhew you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> How to Prognoſticate what winds will blow.</head>
               <p>THat this may be known, for 'tis not only poſſible, but alſo probable, be pleaſed to take notice of theſe few particulars following:</p>
               <p>In the Figure of the Suns ingreſſe into any of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal Signs, or <hi>Conjunction</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> of the Luminaries preceeding and ſucceeding, or any Monthly Lunations; obſerve carefully what Planet is predominant in the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, his poſition and mutual aſpect (if he hes any) which known, do ſo much but as to take notice what Winds or Quarters of Heaven that Planet (or Planets) ſignifie (together with the ſign he is poſited in) &amp; that you may not be miſtaken herein; before I go further, I will here ſhow you the principal Quarters of Heaven, which the Planets ſignifie, by which you may (at all times) be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to give a more then probable conjecture, which way the wind will blow, For,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> is mover of the Eaſtern winds, <hi>Jupiter,</hi> of the Northern, <hi>Mars</hi> of the Weſt and Southern, <hi>Venus</hi> of the Southern, <hi>Mercury</hi> according to the nature of that or thoſe Planets he is joyned with, or aſpected to; the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries are movers of the Weſtern winds, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:66102:33"/>
               <p>The quality of the winds and their bearing is alſo known from Planets poſitions in the Figure; for thoſe Planets with Latitude and South Declination, from the <hi>Medium Coeli</hi> moves the Southern winds to blow; from the <hi>Imum Coeli</hi> with Latitude and Northern Declination, the North winds: The Oriental Planets move the Eaſtern winds, and the Ocidental the Weſtern wind, and when they be weak, they cauſe the intermediate winds to blow. —Likewiſe the Scituation and Quality of the winds is found from the Latitude of the Moon, as ſhe inclines to the North or South.</p>
               <p>The Signs do alſo demonſtrate the winds as well as the Planets, although the magnitude of their ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be leſſe then the Planets, for they draw down their vertues, and tranſmits it to the Earth: <hi>Aries, Leo</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitary</hi> excite the North-weſt winds; <hi>Taurus, Virgo</hi> and <hi>Capricorny</hi> the South-eaſt, <hi>Gemini, Libra,</hi> and <hi>Aquary</hi> the North-eaſt, <hi>Cancer, Scorpio</hi> and <hi>Piſces</hi> the South-weſt.</p>
               <p>We may in ſome meaſure Prognoſticate the quality of the winds, for if <hi>Mercurius</hi> apply to <hi>Saturn,</hi> it produceth great winds, clouds and rain; if to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſweet winds, if to <hi>Mars,</hi> warm winds; if to the <hi>Sun,</hi> warm and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full winds; if to <hi>Venus,</hi> winds, and ſo I conclude this Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> Of Earth-quakes, Thunders, Lightnings, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their naturall cauſes and ſignifications.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>1. Of the <hi>Rain-bow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Rain-bow is the ſhining and rebounding of beams of light, which turn to the contrary vapour again in the cloud, which is oppoſite to the Sun; and ſo according to the diverſity of the thinneſſe of that cloud do the beams appear, red above, yellow in the midle, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66102:33"/> green in the lower parts, but in themſelves all this while they have no real colour, that is a true colour. Here note, that the neerer the Sun is to the Horizon, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the Rain-bow.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The effects of the <hi>Rain-bow.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If the Rain-bow appear or be viſible in the morning it ſignifies moiſture (unleſſe great drought of the air work the contrary) if in the evening, fair weather; Moreover, if the Rain-bow appear fair, it betokens foul weather, but if it appear foul, look for fair weather, the greener the more rain, the reder the more wind.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>2. Of <hi>Rain.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Rain is a cold vapour, and earthly humour or fumoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties out of water attracted by the clouds: I omit to ſpeak of prodigious and miraculous rains, as Milk, Blood, Fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They who deſire to read ſuck like, ſee <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 58.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>3. Of <hi>Froſt</hi> and <hi>Dew.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>It is a cold moiſt vapour, drawn up in the day by the faint heat of the Sun, and deſcends again in the night, where it is either congealed (as in Winter) or reſolved into water (as in Summer) Froſt in the Spring or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt is a ſign of fair weather.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>4. Of <hi>Snow.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Snow is a moiſt vapour, drawn up to the midle Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Air, then thickened and frozen into the body of a Cloud, and ſo congealed, deſcendeth into Fleeces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>5. Of <hi>Haill.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Haill is a Cloud reſolved into water, congeals in its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion, the higher it comes, and the longer it tarrieth in the Air, the rounder is the Haill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>6. Of <hi>Winds.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Winds is a multitude of dry exhalations drawn up from the earth, enforcing it ſelf here and there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>7. Of <hi>Earth-quakes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Plenty of Winds, entered into Holes or Caves of the Earth, which being abſent from above the Earth (cauſeth quietneſſe) at laſt their violent burſting out (the earth ſudden by cloſing again) cauſeth the Earthquake.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:66102:34"/>
                  <head>8. Tokens of <hi>Earth-quakes</hi> to come.</head>
                  <p>A fiery clould appearing in the Element like a little Pillar. The obſcurity and darkneſſe of the Sun (without Clouds) and ſtrangely coloured, as bloody, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Earthquakes to come. Alſo when deep Well waters are ſeen to tremble at the bottome; or if the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters there be infected: Alſo a great quietneſſe by Sea and Land, and eſpecially long abſence of Winds. Moreover, ſtrange ſights and apparitions in the Air: or the noiſe and clamours (as it were) of men in the Clouds, ruſhings of Harneſſe, Mournings and Lamentations, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>9. Of <hi>Thunders.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Thunder is the quenching of fire in a cloud, or a hot and dry exhalation mixed with moiſture, carried up to the midle Region, and wrapping it ſelf in a cloud which is moiſt, there ariſeth a ſtrife; the heat beating, and with a mighty violence breaketh the ſides of the cloud with a thundering noiſe; the fire diſperſes and flaſhes, thence comes the lightning.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The ſignification of <hi>Thunder.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="10">10. Thunders in the morning ſignifieth wind, about noon rain, in the evening great tempeſts. —Some write that Sundayes thunder, ſignifieth the death of Learned men: Mundayes, the death of women: Tueſdayes, the plenitude of corn and grain: Wedneſdayes, the death of harlots, and bloodſhed: Thurſday, plenty of ſheep and corn: Fryday, the ſlaughter of a great man, and other horrible murders: Saturndayes thunder, a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Peſtilent Plague, and great dearth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of <hi>Comets</hi> and their ſignifications.</head>
                  <p>A Comet is a Flame working in a dry and hot exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, drawn up to the higheſt part of the Air: its mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or ſubſtance after it's burnt and diſperſed, provoketh winds, it ſignifieth corruptions in the Air, Earthquakes, Wars, dearth of Corn, a common Death of man and Beaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>12. Of the <hi>Whirlewind.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Whirlewind is a moſt ſudden and violent blaſt, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth from the narrow paſſages of the Clouds, as it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66102:34"/> were winding, is vehemently carried and daſhed againſt the earth, and ſo riſeth back like a Ball, windeth about what it findeth, and bearing aloft all that's within its power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> Containing ſeveral Propoſitions in Aſtronomy.</head>
               <p>THeſe few Propoſitions which I intend here to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, be ſuch as are of ordinary and frequent uſe in the practice of the Mathematicks, and ſuch as I hold fit and requiſit for all them to know who ſhall make uſe of this Treatiſe.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 1. To find the Suns Declination.</head>
                  <p>As the Radius is to the ſine of the Suns greateſt Decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo is the fine of his diſtance from the next Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial Point, to the ſine of his Declination required, which is North if the Sun be in <hi>Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo</hi> and <hi>Virgo,</hi> and ſouth when he is in <hi>Libra, Scorpio, Sagitary, Capricorn, Aquary</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition.</hi> 2. To find the Suns right Aſcenſion.</head>
                  <p>As the Radius, is to the Tangent of the Suns Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſo the Co-fine of his greateſt Declination, to the Tangent of his right Aſcenſion required.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 3. To find the Aſcenſional Difference.</head>
                  <p>As the Co-tangent of the Latitude, is to the Radius, ſo is the Tangent of his Declination, to the ſine of his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Difference.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 4. To find the Suns Amplitude.</head>
                  <p>As the Co-ſine of the Latitude, is to the Radius, ſo is the ſine of the Suns Declination, to the ſine of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude required.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:66102:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 5. To find the time when the Sun will be due Eaſt and Weſt.</head>
                  <p>As the Tangent of the Latitude, is to the Radius, ſo the Tangent of the Declination, to the Co-ſine of the hour from the Meridian, when he will be due Eaſt or Weſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 6. To find the Suns Altitude when he is due Eaſt or Weſt.</head>
                  <p>As the ſine of the Latitude, is to the Radius, ſo is the ſine of the Suns Declination, to the ſine of his Altitude, when he is due Eaſt or Weſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 7. To find the Suns Altitude at the hour of ſix.</head>
                  <p>As the Radius, is to the ſine of the Latitude, ſo is the ſine of the Suns Declination, to the ſine of the Suns Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, at the hour of ſix as was required.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 8. To find the Suns Altitude at any time aſſigned.</head>
                  <p>In this Propoſition there be two caſes; For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If he be in the Aequator, ſay, — As the Radius, is to the Co-ſine of his diſtance from the Meridian, ſo is the Co-ſine of the Latitude, to the ſine of his Altitude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When the Sun hath either North or South Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As the Radius, is to the Co-tangent of the Latitude, ſo the Co-ſine of his diſtance from the Meridian, to the Tangent of ane Arch, which ſubſtracted from the Suns diſtance from the Pole, leaveth a ſecond Arch. Then ſay,</p>
                  <p>As the Co-ſine of the firſt Arch, is to the Coſine of the ſecond Arch, ſo is the ſine of the Latitude, to the ſine of the Suns Altitude, as was required.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 9. To find the Suns Azimuth.</head>
                  <p>As the Co-ſine of the Suns Altitude, is to the ſine of his diſtance from the Meridian, ſo is the ſine of his diſtance from the Pole, to the ſine of his Azimuth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:66102:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 10. To find the Declination, right Aſcenſion and Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional difference of the Planets or fixed Stars.</head>
                  <p>Suppoſe the place of any Planet be given in Longitude and Latitude: As ſuppoſe the Moon were the Planet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed her true place given, let be <hi>Leo,</hi> 20 d. 49 m. 53 ſ. and her Latitude 00 d. 22 m. 52 ſ. North (as at the time of that ſolar Eclipſe, which will happen in <hi>July</hi> 1684.) which being given with the greateſt obliquity of the Ecliptique, 23 d. 31 m. 30 ſ. we ſhall enquire for the Moons declination thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label">d.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                           <cell role="label">ſ.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>As the Radius,</cell>
                           <cell>90</cell>
                           <cell>00</cell>
                           <cell>00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Is to the ſ. of the Moons Longitude ab. <hi>Ariete,</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>110</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>53</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>So is the Tangent of the greateſt obliq.</cell>
                           <cell>23</cell>
                           <cell>31</cell>
                           <cell>30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>To the Tangent of an Arch.</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>24</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Then from the Radius,</cell>
                           <cell>90</cell>
                           <cell>00</cell>
                           <cell>00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Subſtract the <hi>Moons</hi> latitude (becauſe its North)</cell>
                           <cell>00</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>57</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Reſts diſtance of the <hi>Moon</hi> from the Pole</cell>
                           <cell>89</cell>
                           <cell>37</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>From which Subſtract the firſt Arch</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>24</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Reſts a ſecond Arch</cell>
                           <cell>67</cell>
                           <cell>28</cell>
                           <cell>44</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Then I ſay again;</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>As the Coſine of the firſt Arch</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>24</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Is to the Coſine of the ſecond Arch</cell>
                           <cell>67</cell>
                           <cell>28</cell>
                           <cell>44</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>So is the Coſine of the greateſt obliq.</cell>
                           <cell>23</cell>
                           <cell>31</cell>
                           <cell>30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>To the ſine of the <hi>Moons</hi> declination required</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                           <cell>50</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2. To find the <hi>Moons</hi> right aſcenſion, I ſay,</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>As the Coſine of the <hi>Moons</hi> declination</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                           <cell>50</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Is to the Coſine of the <hi>Moons</hi> longitude, <hi>ab Ariete</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>110</cell>
                           <cell>49</cell>
                           <cell>53</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>So is the ſine of her diſtance from the Pole</cell>
                           <cell>89</cell>
                           <cell>37</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>To the ſine of an Arch, viz.</cell>
                           <cell>22</cell>
                           <cell>36</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which added to 90 degrees, becauſe the <hi>Moon</hi> is in the ſecond Quadrant of the Ecliptique, (and to 180 deg. when in the third Quadrant, &amp;c.) the Aggregate 112 deg. 36 min. 2 ſec. is the right aſcenſion of the <hi>Moon,</hi> as was required.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Her aſcenſional difference is to be found accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the third Propoſition aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:66102:36"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Propoſition</hi> 11. To find the oblique aſcenſions and deſcenſions of the Planets and fixed Stars for any time aſſigned.</head>
                  <p>In this Propoſition there be two Caſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If the declination of the Planet or Star (given) be North, ſubſtract the aſcenſional difference from the right aſcenſion, and the reſidue will be the Planets (or Stars) oblique aſcenſion, but if you adde them, the aggregate will be his oblique deſcenſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Planets declination be South, add the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional difference and right aſcenſion together, the ſum will be the Planets oblique aſcenſion, but if you ſubſtract it, the remainder will be the Planets oblique deſcenſion.</p>
                  <p>As in the former Example, the right aſcenſion of the <hi>Moon</hi> is 112 deg. 36 min. 2 ſec. and her aſcenſional diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence 37 deg. 26 m. 31 ſec. Now becauſe the <hi>Moons</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination is North, I ſubſtract the aſcenſional difference from the right aſcenſion, and the reſidue 75 deg. 9 min. 31 ſec. is the Moons oblique aſcenſion; Likewiſe, I add the aſcenſional difference to the right aſcenſion, and the aggregate 150 deg. 2 min. 33 ſec. is the Moons oblique deſcenſion as was required.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> To find the true time of the Suns riſing and ſetting, with the length of the day and night for any day of the Moneth aſſigned.</head>
               <p>ALthough I could preſcribe ſeveral Rules for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this Queſtion, yet I ſhall for your greater facility) make choyce of that which I ſuppoſe to be moſt familiar and eaſie, as by the Examples follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will appear.</p>
               <p>Enter the following Table with the 5, 10, 15, 20, 25 or 30 day of your Month, finding your dayes (aforeſaid) on the top, and moneths on the margent, and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66102:36"/> Angle, you will find (by inſpection) the exact time of the Suns riſing the ſaid dayes, and by the Rule of Proportion for any other intermediate day.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A Table ſhewing the exact time of the Suns riſing every fifth day, exactly calculated for the Latitude of 56. degrees, 20. min.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Names of the Months</cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="6">The dayes of each Moneth. </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">5 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">10 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">15 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">20 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">25 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">30 day</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ianuary</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8 21</cell>
                        <cell>8 12</cell>
                        <cell>8 3</cell>
                        <cell>7 53</cell>
                        <cell>7 42</cell>
                        <cell>7 29</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>February</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7 18</cell>
                        <cell>7 6</cell>
                        <cell>6 55</cell>
                        <cell>6 43</cell>
                        <cell>6 31</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>March</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6 12</cell>
                        <cell>6 0</cell>
                        <cell>5 48</cell>
                        <cell>5 36</cell>
                        <cell>5 24</cell>
                        <cell>5 10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>April</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4 58</cell>
                        <cell>4 48</cell>
                        <cell>4 36</cell>
                        <cell>4 26</cell>
                        <cell>4 15</cell>
                        <cell>4 5</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>May</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3 55</cell>
                        <cell>3 47</cell>
                        <cell>3 39</cell>
                        <cell>3 32</cell>
                        <cell>3 26</cell>
                        <cell>3 21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iune</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3 18</cell>
                        <cell>3 17</cell>
                        <cell>3 18</cell>
                        <cell>3 23</cell>
                        <cell>3 23</cell>
                        <cell>3 28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iuly</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3 35</cell>
                        <cell>3 42</cell>
                        <cell>3 50</cell>
                        <cell>3 59</cell>
                        <cell>4 9</cell>
                        <cell>4 19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Auguſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4 32</cell>
                        <cell>4 42</cell>
                        <cell>4 54</cell>
                        <cell>5 5</cell>
                        <cell>5 17</cell>
                        <cell>5 28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>September</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5 42</cell>
                        <cell>5 54</cell>
                        <cell>6 3</cell>
                        <cell>6 17</cell>
                        <cell>6 29</cell>
                        <cell>6 41</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>October</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6 52</cell>
                        <cell>7 4</cell>
                        <cell>7 16</cell>
                        <cell>7 27</cell>
                        <cell>7 38</cell>
                        <cell>7 49</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>November</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8 1</cell>
                        <cell>8 11</cell>
                        <cell>8 20</cell>
                        <cell>8 27</cell>
                        <cell>8 34</cell>
                        <cell>8 39</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>December.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8 42</cell>
                        <cell>8 43</cell>
                        <cell>8 42</cell>
                        <cell>8 40</cell>
                        <cell>8 36</cell>
                        <cell>8 31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell cols="6">Time of the Suns riſing in hours and min.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Example, I deſire to know the exact time of the Suns riſing the 15 day of <hi>April;</hi> I look in the Table for the 15 day, and deſcends the ſaids Column, untill I come againſt the Month given, viz. <hi>April,</hi> and I find 4. 36. viz. 4 hours, 36. min. paſt the Suns riſes the ſaids day. In like manner, the 15 day of <hi>May</hi> the Sun riſes 39. min. paſt 3. in the morning: The 15 of <hi>June,</hi> 18 min. paſt 3 in the morning; The 15 of <hi>July,</hi> 50. min. paſt 3. in the morning, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But if you would know the time of the Suns riſing for any other intermediate day, take the difference, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66102:37"/> work by the Golden Rule, and you ſhall find the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall part to be added.</p>
               <p>Example, I deſire to know what time the Sun riſes the 23 of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> I look into the Table, and I find that the Sun riſes the 20 day, at 5 min. paſt 5. and the 25 day, 17 min. paſt 5. the difference is 12 min. Then I ſay— if 5 dayes gives 12 min. What will 3. dayes give? <hi>Anſ.</hi> 7. min. which added to 5 h. 5 min. (the time of the Suns riſing the 20 day) the aggregate is 5 h. 12 min. for the exact time of the Suns riſing the 23 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> as was required.</p>
               <p>If you deſire to know the time of the Suns ſetting, ſubſtract the time of the Suns riſing from 12 hours, and the remainder will be the time of his ſetting.</p>
               <p>Example, I deſire to know the time of the Suns ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the 15 day of <hi>July;</hi> I find that he riſes that day at
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">h.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3 hours 50 min. which known—from</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>I ſubſtract the time of Sun riſing (the 15 of <hi>July</hi>)</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſts the exact time of Sun ſeting the 15 of <hi>July</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Having thus found the time of the Suns ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, if you double the ſame, you have the whole length of the day, whoſe complement to 24 hours, is the length of the night, as in the Example preceeding.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">h.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Suns ſemidiurnal arch, or time of's ſeting</cell>
                        <cell>8.</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>which doubled, gives the length of the day</cell>
                        <cell>16.</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Whoſe Complement to</cell>
                        <cell>24.</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Is the noctural arch, or length of the night</cell>
                        <cell>7.</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>This is ſo plain, that he which underſtands it not, his ignorance out-weighs his wit, as much as a Milſton out-weighs a Feather, and conſequently incapable of Subli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Arts and Sciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:66102:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> To find the <hi>Golden-Numbers, Epacts,</hi> and age of the Moon for any year of God aſſign'd.</head>
               <p n="1">1. TO find the Golden-Number, add 1. to the number of years given, the aggregate divide by 19. the remainder is the Golden Number, required.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To find the Epact, multiply the Golden Number (ſo found as aforeſaid) by 11, the Product divide by 30. the remainder is the Epact, required.</p>
               <p>Example, <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 1698. I demand the Golden Number and Epact for the ſaids year?</p>
               <p>To 1698. I add 1. the aggregate 1699. I divide by 19. reſts (by the quotient) 8. for the Golden Number, which multiplyed by a 11. the Product is 88. this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by 30. the remainder (beſides the quotient) is 28. and ſo much is the Epact of the ſaids year 1698. as was required.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To know the age of the Moon at all times: Find firſt the Epact for that year, and unto it add the number of the dayes of the Month, and the Moneths from <hi>March</hi> (counting <hi>March</hi> for one) and the aggregate (if it be leſs then 30.) is the age of the Moon, required.</p>
               <p>Example, I demand the age of the Moon the 20 day of <hi>September</hi> 1664. firſt I find the Epact for that year (either by the former Rule, or by the Table following) to be 12. to which I add 20. (the day of the Moneth aſſign'd) the ſum is 32. to which I add the number of Moneths from <hi>March,</hi> (calling <hi>March</hi> one, <hi>April</hi> two, <hi>May</hi> three, &amp;c.) which is 7. the aggregate is 39. from which I deduct 29. reſts 19. for the age of the Moon the 20 of <hi>September</hi> 1664. as was required.— The operation.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The day of the given Moneth</cell>
                        <cell>20 dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The number of months from <hi>March</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7 dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Epact of the year aſſign'd</cell>
                        <cell>12 dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Aggregate</cell>
                        <cell>39 dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Common Lunar revolution. ſubſt.</cell>
                        <cell>29 dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſts the age of the Moon, required</cell>
                        <cell>19 dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:66102:38"/>
               <p>But becauſe every one cannot Multiply and Divide, that thereby they might find the Golden Numbers and Epacts, and conſequently the Age of the Moon: I have therefore compoſed the following Table, which (by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection only) will ſhew you all the Golden Numbers, Epacts, Sudayes Letters, and Whitſundayes for 51 years to come, beginning <hi>Anno</hi> 1662. ending <hi>Anno</hi> 1713.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Years of Chriſt</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Gol. num.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Epact.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Sun. lett.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Whitſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1662</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>May 18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1663</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>June 7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1664</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>cb</cell>
                        <cell>May 29</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1665</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>May 14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1666</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>June 3</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1667</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>May 26</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1668</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>ed</cell>
                        <cell>May 10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1669</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>May 30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1670</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>May 22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1671</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>June 11</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1672</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>gf</cell>
                        <cell>May 26</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1673</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>May 18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1674</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>June 7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1675</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>May 23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1676</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>ba</cell>
                        <cell>May 14</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1677</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>June 3</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1678</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>May 19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1679</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>June 8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1680</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>dc</cell>
                        <cell>May 30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1681</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>May 22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1682</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>June 4</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1683</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>May 27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1684</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>fe</cell>
                        <cell>May 18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1685</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>June 7</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1686</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>May 23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1687</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>May 15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1688</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>ag</cell>
                        <cell>June 3</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1689</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>May 19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1690</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>June 8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1691</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>May 31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1692</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>cb</cell>
                        <cell>May 15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1693</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>June 4</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1694</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>May 27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1695</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>May 12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1696</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>ed</cell>
                        <cell>May 31</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1697</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>May 23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1698</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>June 12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1699</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>May 28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1700</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>gf</cell>
                        <cell>May 19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1701</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>June 8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1702</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>May 24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1703</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>May 16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1704</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>ba</cell>
                        <cell>June 4</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1705</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>May 27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1706</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>May 12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1707</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>June 1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1708</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>dc</cell>
                        <cell>May 23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1709</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>June 12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1710</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>a</cell>
                        <cell>May 28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1711</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>May 20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1712</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>fe</cell>
                        <cell>June 8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1713</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>May 24</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:66102:38"/>
               <p>The uſe of this Table is this, find the year of God in the Table, and over againſt it, you have (1) the Golden Number: (2.) The Epact: (3.) The Sunday Letter: And (4.) the Month and Day when Whitſunday falls: I ſhall Illuſtrate it by an Example or two.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the year of Chriſt given were 1665. againſt 1665. In the Table I find (1.) 13 for the Golden Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: (2.) 23 for the Epact: (3.) A, for the Sunday Letter: And (4.) <hi>May</hi> the 14 for Whitſunday. — In like manner, if the years aſſigned were 1698. the Golden Number is 8. the Epaſt is 28. the Sunday Letter B. and Whitſunday falls that year on the 12 of <hi>June,</hi> &amp;c. More Examples were ſuperfluous.</p>
               <p>Here note, that where you find two Dominical Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it ſignifieth that year is Leap-year, and therefore you are to take the firſt of them for <hi>January</hi> and <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and the ſecond Letter for all the year after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIV.</hi> To find the time of the Moons riſing and ſetting, and how long She ſhines.</head>
               <p>BY the true places of the Luminaries, find their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Aſcenſions (according to the 21 Chapter, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> 11.) Which being known, ſubſtract the oblique Aſcenſion of the Sun, from the oblique Aſcenſion of the Moon, and the Arch remaining converted into time, and added to the time of the Suns riſing, the Aggregate will be the exact time of the Moon (or Stars) riſing as was required. But becauſe every one who peruſeth this Book, cannot underſtand this direction, nor properly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſame to practice. I ſhall therefore make choiſe of that way which I know to be moſt familiar and eaſie for the benefit of all men: Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Firſt find the Age of the Moon according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Chapter: with which enter the following Table, and ye ſhall find againſt it the hours and minuts of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:66102:39"/> the Moons ſhining, which is to be added to the time of the Suns riſing, if the Moon be encreaſing in light. But to be ſubſtracted if ſhe be decreaſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo the Sum or difference will be the time of the Moons riſing.</p>
               <p>Example, I demand what time the Moon riſes the 5 of <hi>January,</hi> 1662? the ſaids day the Moon is 25 dayes old, (according to my <hi>Mercurius Coelicus</hi> pag. 15. lately emited for the year 1662.) with which I enter the following Table, and I find that the Moon ſhines 4. h. 00 m. then I look in the 22 Chapter what time the Sun riſes the 5. of <hi>January,</hi> which I find at 8 h. 21 m. Now becauſe the Moon is decreaſing in light, therefore I ſubſtract 4 h. 00 m. (the time that the Moon ſhineth) from 8 h. 21 m. (the time of the Suns riſing) reſts 4 h. 21 m. hence I conclude, that the Moon riſes 21 min. 4. in the morning the 5 of <hi>January</hi> 1662.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Moons Age encreaſing.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">The time that the Moon ſhineth.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Moons Age decreaſing.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0 48</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1 36</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2 24</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>3 10</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>4 0</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>4 48</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>5 36</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>6 24</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>7 10</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>8 0</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>8 48</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>9 36</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>10 24</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>11 10</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>12 0</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall add another example for practice. The 14 day of <hi>February</hi> 1662. the Moon is 6 dayes old, with which I enter this annexed Table, and I find that the Moon ſhineth 4 h. 48 min. Then I look for the time of the Suns riſing the 14 day of <hi>February,</hi> which I find (by making proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) at 6 h. 57 m. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Moon is encreaſing (in light) therefore I adde 4 h. 48 min. to 6 h. 57 min. The Sum is a 11 h. 45 min. Wherefore I conclude, that the Moon riſeth (the 14 day of <hi>February</hi> 1662.) at 45 m. paſt a 11 in the forenoon, that is 15 m. <hi>Ante meridiem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you be deſirous to know the time of the Moons ſetting.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66102:39"/> Then to the time of the Suns ſetting, add the time of her ſhining (if ſhe be encreaſing) Or ſubſtract the ſame (if ſhe be decreaſing) to; or from the time of the Suns ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and the ſum or difference will be the time of her ſetting: this is ſo plain, that an example were ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> To find the Dominical Letters, and dayes of the Week that begins every Moneth, and Moveable Feaſts for ever.</head>
               <p>TO find the Dominical Letters for ever, I have inſert the following Table: Upon each ſide whereof ye have firſt the Dominical Letters: And ſecondly, the years of God reſpectively, which Inchoats at 1661. and continues till 1688. Where you are to note, that 1688. begins another new Period of years: ſo that you are to place (if need be) 1689. in ſtead of 1661. and 1690. in place of 1662. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The uſe of this Table is to find the Dominical Letters, and dayes of the Week that begins every Moneth, and conſequently what day of the Week any day of the Moneth happens upon.</p>
               <p>As for Example, in the year 1667. I find that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minical Letter is F. This Dominical Letter F, I find likewiſe amongſt the lower Dominical Letters, at the bottome of the Table, and under it is M, for Munday: Wherefore I conclude, that the firſt Munday of <hi>Aprile</hi> or <hi>July</hi> falls upon the firſt day, the ſecond Munday upon the 8 day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So after this manner may be found the time that every Munday falls through the Moneths: As alſo, the dayes of the Week that any day of the Moneth happens on, by obſerving the dayes under the reſpective Moneths through the year.</p>
               <p>I told you before, that wherever you find two Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minical Letters, it is Leap year, and that you are to take
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66102:40"/> the firſt of them for <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> and the next for all the year after. As for Example, the year 1680. D, directs you to Wedneſday for the Months of <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February,</hi> and C, to Thurſday for all the year after.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Dom. Let.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Year God.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>July April</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Sept. Dece.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>June</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>mar. feb. no.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Auguſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>May</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Octob. Jan.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Year God.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Domi. Let.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>AG / F</cell>
                        <cell>1688/1661</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>1674 1675</cell>
                        <cell>D C</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>E D</cell>
                        <cell>1662 1663</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>1676 1677</cell>
                        <cell>BA G</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>OB A</cell>
                        <cell>1664 1665</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>1678 1679</cell>
                        <cell>F E</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>G F</cell>
                        <cell>1666 1667</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>1680 1681</cell>
                        <cell>DC B</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ED C</cell>
                        <cell>1668 1669</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>1682 1683</cell>
                        <cell>A G</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>B A</cell>
                        <cell>1670 1671</cell>
                        <cell>G</cell>
                        <cell>F</cell>
                        <cell>E</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>C</cell>
                        <cell>B</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell>1684 1685</cell>
                        <cell>FE D</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>GF E</cell>
                        <cell>1672 1673</cell>
                        <cell>S</cell>
                        <cell>M</cell>
                        <cell>T</cell>
                        <cell>W</cell>
                        <cell>T</cell>
                        <cell>F</cell>
                        <cell>S</cell>
                        <cell>1686 1687</cell>
                        <cell>C B</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, to find the Moveable Feaſts,</p>
               <p>Seek the Change of the Moon in <hi>February,</hi> for that year in which ye deſire to know when any of the Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Feaſts happens, and not upon what day the Change falls; for the next Tueſday is Shrove-Tueſday, or vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly called Faſtens. Even; but if the Change of the Moon happen on Tueſday, then the next Tueſday ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66102:40"/> is it. The next Sunday is the firſt Sunday in Lent, ſix Sundayes after is Eaſter day, commonly called Paſch day, and the ſeventh Sunday after that is Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday. This is ſo plain that it needs no Example.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> Of the deſcription of the Quadrant, and how to find the Altitude of the Sun, Moon or Stars thereby.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a quadrant</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Laſtly, If you divide each of theſe 18 into 5, the total will be 90 degrees. Which (you may ſub-divide if quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity will give live) numbred from the left hand towards the right, marking it with 10, 20, 30, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unto 90 after the uſual manner.</p>
               <p>As for the Square within, ye ſhall draw from either ſide of your Quadrant a right Line, cutting one another at right Angles at the midle of the Quadrant, which is 45 degrees. This Scale or Square you may divide into 12, 60, 100, or 1000, (the more the better and more commodious) equal parts, all marked from the Center A. That ſide of the Square next the ſights, is called, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra recta,</hi> or parts of right ſhaddow. The other ſide is called, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra verſa,</hi> or points of contrary ſhaddow.</p>
               <p>To this Quadrant (as to all others of this kind in their uſe) you muſt place two ſights upon the Line A C, with a Line and Plummet, hanging up in the Center A, and ſo your Quadrant is finiſhed.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Now to find the Altitude of the Sun, Moon or Stars thereby.</head>
                  <p>HOld up your Quadrant to the Sun (the Threed and Plummet having their free courſe hanging in the Center A,) moving it up or down, untill you ſee that both the ſights have received the Sun Beams: At which inſtant mark the fall of the Line and Plummet, for it will cut (upon the Limb of your Quadrant) the degree and minut of the Suns Altitude, at the time of your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
                  <p>But if you deſire (in the night time) to find the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66102:41"/> Altitude of the Planets or fixed Stars, then ſet the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant to your eye, looking through both the ſights, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you eſpy that Planet or Star whoſe Altitude you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, which having found, your Plummer hanging at liberty, mark the fall thereof upon the Quadrants Limb, and it will ſhow you the Altitude of that Coeleſtial Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as you required.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> How to finde the Altitude of any Tower, Caſtle or Steeple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF I ſhould endeavour to inſtruct you by Precept and Example, in every various Scituation and Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that might be propoſed, for attaining the true heights of Towers, Caſtles, Steeples or Hills, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Quadrant, I ſhould exceed my intention in this place, for it would require a peculiar Treatiſe by it ſelf (which I may happily publiſh, if God continue my life) And therefore I ſhall (here in this Chapter) only ſhew you, how (by your Quadrant, with, and without Calculation) to know all heights acceſſible,</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Firſt, by Calculation.</head>
                  <p>Lift up your Quadrant towards the Tower or Steeple whoſe Altitude you require, untill you behold (through both the ſights) the very Summity or Top; which found, mark well the Diviſions or Points in your Square, which the Threed and Plummet did fall on: And if they be of right ſhaddow (that is to ſay when the Threed and Plummet falls on that ſide of the Square which is next the ſights) Then ſay, As the Parts out, is to the whole Scale. So is the length of the Baſe, to the Altitude of the Tower: And therefore multiply the diſtance from you to the Baſe by 12. the product divide by the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66102:42"/> parts cut (by the fall of the Plummet) the Quotient will ſhow you the Altitude required. — But if the Threed fall upon the contrary ſhaddow, then ſay, As the whole Scale is to the parts cut, So is the length of the Baſe, to the Altitude required. And therefore multiply the Baſe by the parts cut, the product divide by the whole Scale, and the Quotient is your deſired Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude above the Level of your Eye.</p>
                  <p>Example, Suppoſe the Threed with the Plummet ſhould happen to fall on 6 parts of contrary ſhaddow, and the diſtance from your ſtanding to the Baſe of the Tower be 120 foot: I ſay,— As the whole Scale 12, is to the parts cut 6, So is the length of the Baſe 120 foot, to the Altitude of the Tower 60 foot. Thus mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying the Baſe 120, by the parts cut 6, the product 720 divided by 12, the Quotient is juſt 60, and ſo many foot high is that Tower or Steeple above the Level of your Eye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Secondly, Without Calculation.</head>
                  <p>Becauſe there may be ſome Ingenious Men, that would know the Altitude of a place, and yet hath no <hi>Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> to Multiply and Divide: therefore to ſatisfie ſuch, I give this Direction. That if the Tower or Steeple, &amp;c. be acceſſible, then hold your Quadrant up towards it, looking diligently through both the ſights, going back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or forward, untill the Line of the Plummet fall on 45 degrees. Which found, Meaſure the diſtance between your ſtanding and the Baſe, for that is the juſt Altitude of the Tower, above the Level of your Eye, as you required.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> How to find out the Latitude of a place, or the Poles Elevation above the Horizon.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt diligently attend with your Quadrant about noon, to find the Suns Meridian Altitude,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:66102:42"/> which you may eaſily do, by obſerving carefully a little before noon, and a little after, untill you perceive the Sun begin to fall again, then marking what was his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Meridian Altitude, reſerve it till anone.</p>
               <p>Then find the Suns declination according to the firſt Propoſition of the 21 Chapter, and conſider whither it be North or South. The declination of the Sun is North, when the day is more then 12 hours long: and South when it's leſſe then 12 hours long. And therefore hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found the Meridian, Altitude and Declination of the Sun, you may eaſily find the Latitude of the place after this manner.</p>
               <p>If the Sun hath North Declination, then ſubſtract his Declination out of his Meridian Altitude, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder will be the Altitude of the Equinoctial, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of your Latitude. But if the Sun hath South Declination, then adde it to his Meridian Altitude: the Aggregate will be the heigth of the Equinoctial, which ſubſtracted from 90 degrees, there will remain the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of your place, or Altitude of the Pole above your Horizon.</p>
               <p>As for Example, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1661. <hi>September</hi> 21. At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> I carefully obſerved the Suns Meridian, Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which I found to be 30 degr. 32 min. At which time the Suns true place was <hi>Libra,</hi> 8 d. 35 m. 45 ſ. And his Declination South, 3 d. 25 m. 12 ſ. Now becauſe the declination is South, I adde it to the Suns Meridian Altitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">d.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Meridian Altitude of the Sun obſerved.</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Suns declination (becauſe it's ſouth) add,</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Agg. is the heighth of the Equinoctial.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Which ſubſtracted from,</cell>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>00</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſts the Latitude of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> viz.</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>03</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Another Example I ſhall give you. In the ſaids year, upon the 10th of <hi>October,</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> I obſerved the Suns Meridian Altitude to be 23 d. 22 min. at which time his true place was <hi>Libra,</hi> 27 d. 26 m. having South Declination, 10 d. 35 m. which ordered as aforeſaid, it giveth the Latitude of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 56 d. 3 m. as before.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:66102:43"/> In theſe Examples, I have purpoſely omittted the Suns Meridian <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis,</hi> becauſe I would not trouble you with ſuch Nyceties; neither is ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſſe neceſſary for every common obſervation; for as it's difficult to obtain (becauſe it requires a peculiar Calculation, which depends upon <hi>Trigonometry</hi>) ſo it's as rarely underſtood amongſt the Vulgar. Nevertheleſs, for the benefit of my Countrey-men, I ſhall in a Chapter by it ſelf, demonſtrate what it is, and alſo how to calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it at all times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> To find the Diameter, Circumference, Solidity and Superficies of any Sphere or Globe.</head>
               <p>TO reſolve theſe Geometrical Propoſitions, I ſhall uſe this Method, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Diameter of any Sphere, Globe, or Circle, being given to find the Circumference thereof.</p>
               <p>Multiply the given Diameter by 22. the Product di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide by 7. the Quotient will ſhew the Circumference required.</p>
               <p>Example, Suppoſe I have a Sphere, Globe, or Circle whoſe Diameter is 14 Inches: I demand how many Inches it is in Circumference? I ſay, as 7 is to 22. ſo is the given Diameter 14. to the required Circumference 44 and ſo many Inches it's round.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Circumference of any Sphere, Globe, or Circle being given to find the Diameter thereof.</p>
               <p>Multiply the given Circumference by 7, the Product divide by 12, the Quotient is the Diameter thereof.</p>
               <p>Example, The Circumference aforeſaid being 44. I demand how much is the Diameter thereof. I ſay, as 22 is to 7. So is the given Circumference 44 Inches, to the required Diameter 14 Inches.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:66102:43"/>3. The Diameter and Circumference of any Sphere, or Globe, being given, to find the Superficies thereof.</p>
               <p>Multiply the Circumference by the Diameter, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct will be the ſuperficies of the Globe or Sphere, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Example, Let the Diameter be 14 Inches, and the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference 44 Inches, the one multiplied by the other, the product is 616 Inches, and ſo much is the ſuperficies of the ſaids Globe or Sphere, as was required.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Diameter of any Sphere or Globe being given to find the Craſitude or Solidity thereof.</p>
               <p>Multiply the given Diameter cubicaly, the product multiply (again) by a 11. the laſt product divided by 21. the Quotient will ſhew the Craſitude required.</p>
               <p>Example, The Diameter of a Sphere or Globe being 14 Inches. I demand how many Inches is contained in its ſolid capacity? — 14 muliplyed cubicaly, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct is 2744. This again by a 11 maketh 30184. which divided by 21. the Quotient is 1437 and 1—3, and ſo many Inches it is in Solidity, or Craſitude, as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <p>Here note, that a Cubical foot (that is 12 Inches every way) contains in it 1728 ſolid Inches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> How to find the weight of a Globe or Ball of Mettal or Stone, without weighing them in Ballances.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Find the ſaid capacity of the Globe or Ball ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly in Inches, as I deſired you in the preceeding Chapter. Secondly, Conſider its Mettal, whither it be Gold, Silver, Braſſe, Iron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or Marble, or ordinary Free-ſtone, find the ſame (whatſoever Mettal it be) in the following Table: and againſt it on the left hand, you will find a Number, and in the top the common Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66102:44"/> of all theſe Mettals which known to find the weight of the Globe or Ball in ounces, I uſe this Analagy.</p>
               <p>As the Radius, is to the ſolid Inches of the Mettal or Stone (named) ſo is the left hand Number of the ſaids Mettal or Stone, to the ounces of the weight thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A moſt excellent Table ſhewing the Weights and Meaſures of all Mettals and Stones.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="3">The common <hi>Radius</hi> is a 1000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Left hand Number.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">Right hand number.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13200</cell>
                        <cell>Gold.</cell>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7880</cell>
                        <cell>Quick-ſilver.</cell>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6798</cell>
                        <cell>Lead.</cell>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6315</cell>
                        <cell>Silver.</cell>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4958</cell>
                        <cell>Braſſe.</cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4333</cell>
                        <cell>Iron.</cell>
                        <cell>230</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4067</cell>
                        <cell>Tin.</cell>
                        <cell>250</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1645</cell>
                        <cell>Marble.</cell>
                        <cell>680</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1420</cell>
                        <cell>Ord. Freeſton.</cell>
                        <cell>710</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Example, I have an Iron Bullet of 8 Inches Diameter which containeth (according to the preceeding Chapter) 268, 1 — 5 ſolid Inches: I demand how many ounces the ſaids Bullet weighs? — I ſay, as the Radius 1000 is to 268, 1 — 5 Inches, ſo is the left hand Number 4333 to 1162 ounces, that is, 72 pound, 10 ounces, as was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. — If the ſame Ball had been Silver, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the weight thereof?</p>
               <p>As the Radius a 1000, is to 268, 1 — 5, ſo is the left hand number 6315 to 1693 ounces (and ſomething more then a half) that is, 105 pound, 13 ounces (and 683— 1000 part of an ounce.)</p>
               <p>In like manner, a round Bullet of ordinary Free-ſtone of 8 Inches Diameter: I demand how much it wil weigh? I ſay, as the Radius 1000, is to 268, 1 — 5 (the ſolid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity) ſo is 1420, to 380, 211 —250, that is, 23 pound, 12 ounces, 13 drop. Hence it appears, that a Silver,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66102:44"/> Iron and ordinary Free-ſtone Bullet, of equal Diameters, weighs as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> Silver 1693 ounces, Iron 1162, and ordinary Free-ſtone 380, by their differences you may find out their ſeveral proportions, which one Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bears to another in bodies of equal Magnitudes and Diameters, by theſe three Examples. You may finde the weight of any material Globe or Bullet of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever bulk, without weighing the ſame in Scales or Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances.</p>
               <p>This Table hath yet another uſe; for if the weight of any Globe or Ball be given in ounces, you may find the ſolid capacity thereof in ounces, thus. As the Radius 1000, is to the weight of the mettall or Stone (named) in ounces, ſo is the right hand Number, to the ſolid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity in Inches.</p>
               <p>Example, An Iron Bullet of 8 Inches Diameter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, weighs 1162 ounces. I demand the number of its ſolid capacity in Inches.— I ſay, as the Radius 1000, is to 1162 ounces, ſo is 230 to 268 <hi>ferè,</hi> the ſolid Inches contained therein. More examples (in a thing ſo plain) were but ſuperfluous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> Of the Planets <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis,</hi> and how to calculate the ſame at all times.</head>
               <p>I Promiſed in the 28 Chapter preceeding, to ſhow you both a Demonſtration of, and alſo by Examples how, to Calculate the <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis</hi> of the Planets, for any time Aſſign'd: And I am now come to perform what I there promiſed, with as much brevity and facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as I can. — Which take as followeth.</p>
               <p>In this Figure, Z, B, A, I, H, repreſents the Meridian, K, C, G, the Orbe of the Sun (or any other Planet) D, the Center of the Earth, E, F, the Superficies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Z, the Zenith. E, I, the Horizon, C, the place of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66102:45"/> Sun (or any other Planet) in his Orbe. The Line, D, C, B, repreſents the planets true place, from the Center of the Earth, in the Meridian at, B. The Line, E, C, A, his apparent place, as it appeareth from us at E. The Angle of the <hi>Paralax</hi> of Altitude, is, A, C, B, (which is equal to E, C, D.) The Angle, A, E, I, is the Angle of the apparent Altitude, of the Planet above the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon (which in this Example we ſuppoſe to be 27 degr. 40 min.) whoſe Complement is, Z, E, A, (62 deg. 20 min.) —Here you may ſee that the apparent Altitude of the Planets, is leſſe from the Superficies (or place of Obſervation at E,) then from the Center of the Earth; (at D,) from which place the Planet in his Orb appears higher in the Meridian at B, then he doth from E, in the Meridian at A, ſo that the Angle of the Planets <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis,</hi> is nothing elſe but the difference between the true and apparent Altitude, in the Meridian or Circle of Altitude.</p>
               <p>Here note, that the nearer a Planet is to the Horizon and Center of the Earth, the greater is the <hi>Paralax</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And hence it is, that the Moon (becauſe of her Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinity to the Earth) hath the greateſt <hi>Paralax</hi> of all the other Planets. And that's a main reaſon why we have ſo few Solar Eclipſes, and thoſe few have ſo little ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity. Becauſe frequently her Southern <hi>Paralax</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds her Northern Latitude (the greateſt Eclipſes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening alwayes when they are equal, and leaſt when her Latitude is South) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe things being premiſed, I come next to practice: And for Illuſtration, I ſhall add an Example of either of the Luminaries, for to find their <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis</hi> at any time Aſſign'd.</p>
               <p>Firſt, an Example in the Sun.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the Altitude of the Sun to be (by obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) 27 deg. 40 min. and his diſtance from the Earth (by calculation) 101798 parts: I demand how much will his <hi>Paralax</hi> of Altitude (then) be? — To reſolve this (and all ſuch like) Queſtions. I return to this annexed Diagram, for Demonſtrations ſake, where, In the Triangle, C, D, E, we have known, [1] E, C,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:66102:45"/> the diſtance of the Sun from the Earth 101798. [2] E, D, the Semidiamiter of the Earth 68, 1—2. [3] The Triangle, C, E, D, 117 d. 40 m. which biſected, gives 58 deg. 50 min. the half ſum of the oppoſite Angles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. Hence to find the <hi>Paralax</hi> of Altitude, A, C, B. Say by this Analagy.</p>
               <p>As the ſum, is to the difference, ſo is the Tangent of the half ſum of the oppoſite Angles unknown, To the Tangent of an Arch: whoſe difference is the <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis</hi> required.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram demonstrating solving for the altitude of the sun</figDesc>
                  <head>The Operation.</head>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>E, C.</cell>
                        <cell>101798,</cell>
                        <cell>0-0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>E, D.</cell>
                        <cell>68,</cell>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <table>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:66102:46"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Logarithm.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sum of E, C, and E, D.</cell>
                        <cell>101866,</cell>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5, 008244</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Difference</cell>
                        <cell>101729,</cell>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5, 007658</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>So is the Tangent of</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>58 d. 50 m. 00 ſ.</cell>
                        <cell>10, 218369</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>15, 226027</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To the Tangent of</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>58. 47. 56.</cell>
                        <cell>10, 217783</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſe difference 2. 4. is the Angle, A, C, B, or the Suns <hi>Paralax</hi> of Altitude as was required.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Example is of the Moon.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe the Altitude of the Moon were found (by Obſervation) to be (as before) 27 deg. 40 min. and her diſtance from the Earth (by Calculation) 3879. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what, or how much will her <hi>Paralax</hi> of Altitude be at the time of the Obſervation?</p>
               <p>In the Triangle C, D, E, the Line C, E, repreſents the diſtance of the Moon from the Earth 3879. the ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> E, D, and Triangle C, D, E, being the ſame as before.</p>
               <p>The Operation is as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>E, C,</cell>
                        <cell>3879,</cell>
                        <cell>0-0</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>E, D,</cell>
                        <cell>68,</cell>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sum of E, C, and E, D,</cell>
                        <cell>3957,</cell>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3,596322</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Difference</cell>
                        <cell>3810,</cell>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3, 580982</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>So is the Tangent of</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>58 d. 50 m. 00 ſ.</cell>
                        <cell>10, 218369</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>13, 799351</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>To the Tangent of</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>57. 55. 47.</cell>
                        <cell>10, 203029</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſe difference 54. 13. is the Angle A, C, B, or <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis</hi> of the Moon at the time of the Obſervation, as was required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> To find the Lord of the hour for any time aſſign'd.</head>
               <p>FIrſt find the time of the Suns riſing (for that day wherein you would know the Lord of the Hour)
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66102:46"/> according to the 24 Chapter: Betwixt which, and the Queſtion propounded or aſſign'd: Find the Intervall of hours and minuts, (which for your greater facility in operation) you may reduce into minuts (by multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your hours by 60.) the product ſhall be your dividend.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Enter the Table following, with your Month on the Margent, and the 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, or 30 day on the top, (taking that day which is neereſt) and in the common angle you will find the length of the Planetary hour that day, which is your Diviſor, by which you are to divide the dividend aforeſaid; the Quotient ſhal ſhew you how many Planets compleatly have ruled, and the remainder (if there be any) is the Planet inſtantly ruling at the time of the Queſtion propounded or aſſign'd: Which to denominate, conſider the day of the week in which the Queſtion is propounded, And,</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Sunday,</hi> give the firſt hour to the <hi>Sun,</hi> the 2 to <hi>Venus,</hi> the 3 to <hi>Mercury,</hi> the 4 to the <hi>Moon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Munday,</hi> give the firſt hour to the <hi>Moon,</hi> the 2 to <hi>Saturn,</hi> the 3 to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the 4 to <hi>Mars,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Tueſday,</hi> give the firſt hour to <hi>Mars,</hi> the 2. to the <hi>Sun,</hi> the 3 to <hi>Venus,</hi> the 4 to <hi>Mercury,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> give the firſt hour to <hi>Mercury,</hi> the 2 to the <hi>Moon,</hi> the 3 to <hi>Saturn,</hi> the 4 to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Thurſday,</hi> give the firſt hour to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the 2 to <hi>Mars,</hi> the 3 to the <hi>Sun,</hi> the 4 to <hi>Venus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Friday,</hi> give the firſt hour to <hi>Venus,</hi> the 2 to <hi>Mercury,</hi> the 3 to the <hi>Moon,</hi> the 4 to <hi>Saturn,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If the day be <hi>Saturnday,</hi> give the firſt hour to <hi>Saturn,</hi> the 2 to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the 3 to <hi>Mars,</hi> the 4 to the <hi>Sun,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo you wil eaſily find that Planet who is Lord of the hour at the time aſſign'd. For illuſtration of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, I ſhall propound an Example, with variety of operations, that you may chooſe the eaſieſt.</p>
               <p>Example, I demand what Planet rules the 5 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> (the day of the week being <hi>Saturnday</hi>) at 45. min. paſt 9 in the morning.</p>
               <p>According to the 24 Chapter, I find that the Sun riſeth
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66102:47"/> the 5 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at 32 min. paſt 4 in the morning. Now becauſe the Queſtion is propounded in the fore-noon, therefore I ſubſtract 4 h. 32 min. (the time of the Suns riſing) from 9 h. 45 min. (the time aſſign'd) reſts 5 h. 13 min. (which is the intevall between the Suns riſing and time of the Queſtion propounded) which I reduce into min (by multiplying by 60) the product is 313 min. for the dividend.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the Table following, againſt the 5 of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> I find that the length of the Planetary hour is, 1 h. 15 min. or 75 min. by which I divide 313. the Quotient is 4 and 13 min. remaining; that is, 4 Planets have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleetly ruled, and the 5 is ruling, which to denominate; the day of the Queſtion being <hi>Saturnday;</hi> I give the firſt hour to <hi>Saturn,</hi> the 2 to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the 3 to <hi>Mars,</hi> the 4 to the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the 13 min. remaining to <hi>Venus:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, that <hi>Venus</hi> is Lady of the hour (at the time of the Queſtion propounded) and hath ruled 13 min. of her time.—this is the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A moſt excellent Table of the length of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netary hours, for the Latitude of <hi>56</hi> d. <hi>20</hi> m.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Names of the Months.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">5 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">10 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">15 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">20 day</cell>
                        <cell role="label">25 day </cell>
                        <cell role="label">30 day</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H. M.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>January</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 36</cell>
                        <cell>0 37</cell>
                        <cell>0 39</cell>
                        <cell>0 41</cell>
                        <cell>0 43</cell>
                        <cell>0 45</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>February</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 47</cell>
                        <cell>0 49</cell>
                        <cell>0 51</cell>
                        <cell>0 53</cell>
                        <cell>0 55</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>March</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 58</cell>
                        <cell>1 0</cell>
                        <cell>1 2</cell>
                        <cell>1 4</cell>
                        <cell>1 6</cell>
                        <cell>1 8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>April</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1 10</cell>
                        <cell>1 12</cell>
                        <cell>1 14</cell>
                        <cell>1 16</cell>
                        <cell>1 18</cell>
                        <cell>1 20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>May</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1 21</cell>
                        <cell>1 22</cell>
                        <cell>1 23</cell>
                        <cell>1 25</cell>
                        <cell>1 26</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>June</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1 27</cell>
                        <cell>1 27</cell>
                        <cell>1 27</cell>
                        <cell>1 26</cell>
                        <cell>1 26</cell>
                        <cell>1 25</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>July</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1 24</cell>
                        <cell>1 23</cell>
                        <cell>1 22</cell>
                        <cell>1 20</cell>
                        <cell>1 18</cell>
                        <cell>1 16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Auguſt</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1 15</cell>
                        <cell>1 13</cell>
                        <cell>1 11</cell>
                        <cell>1 9</cell>
                        <cell>1 7</cell>
                        <cell>1 5</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>September</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1 3</cell>
                        <cell>0 1</cell>
                        <cell>0 59</cell>
                        <cell>0 57</cell>
                        <cell>0 55</cell>
                        <cell>0 53</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>October</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 51</cell>
                        <cell>1 49</cell>
                        <cell>0 47</cell>
                        <cell>0 45</cell>
                        <cell>0 43</cell>
                        <cell>0 42</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>November</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 40</cell>
                        <cell>0 38</cell>
                        <cell>0 37</cell>
                        <cell>0 35</cell>
                        <cell>0 34</cell>
                        <cell>0 34</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>December</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>0 33</cell>
                        <cell>0 33</cell>
                        <cell>0 33</cell>
                        <cell>0 33</cell>
                        <cell>0 34</cell>
                        <cell>0 35</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell cols="6">Length of the Planetary hour in h. and m.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:66102:47"/>
               <p>Variety in operation, the ſecond is more brief by the <hi>Logarithmes,</hi> thus:
<table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Logarith.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Interval between the Sun riſing, and time of the Queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded: reduced, is</cell>
                        <cell>313</cell>
                        <cell>2. 495544</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Length of the Planetary hour in min.</cell>
                        <cell>75</cell>
                        <cell>1. 875061</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Reſts the number of Planets that have ruled, compleet, <hi>viz.</hi> 4.</cell>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>0. 620483</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>The third, laſt, and eaſieſt of all, is this operation fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, the day of the week being <hi>Saturnday, Saturn</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">h.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">m.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>At the Suns riſing, viz.</cell>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>32.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>And continues to rule</cell>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell> length Planetary h.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Untill</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>47 </cell>
                        <cell>ſum</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Then <hi>Jupiter</hi> begins</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>15 </cell>
                        <cell>add</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>And rules till</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>02 </cell>
                        <cell>ſum</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Then <hi>Mars</hi> begins</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>15 </cell>
                        <cell>add</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>and rules till</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>17 </cell>
                        <cell>ſum</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Then <hi>Sol</hi> begins</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell> add</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>and rules till</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>at which time <hi>Venus</hi> begins to rule. </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table> This is the moſt eaſie way of all others; for it requires neither Multiplication nor Diviſion, but performed only by a continual addition of the length of the Planetary hour, to the time of the Suns riſing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you come to the time propounded, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> Shewing what Moon makes full Sea in moſt Sea-Port Towns in <hi>Scotland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="1">1. A South or North Moon makes full ſea at <hi>Queen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, Southampton, Portſ-mouth,</hi> Iſle of <hi>Wight Beachy,</hi> the <hi>Spilts, Kentiſh-knock,</hi> half tide at <hi>Dunkirk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A South by weſt, or North by eaſt Moon, makes full
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:66102:48"/> ſea at <hi>Aberdeen, Rocheſter, Malden, Redban,</hi> and weſt end of the <hi>Black-tail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A South ſouthweſt, or North northeaſt Moon, at <hi>Graves-end, Downs, Rumney, Tenet, Silly</hi> half tide; <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Ramkins, Fernhead, Leith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. A Southweſt by ſouth, or Northeaſt by north Moon at <hi>Dundee,</hi> St. <hi>Andrews, Lisbane,</hi> St. <hi>Lucas, Bell</hi> Iſle, <hi>Holy</hi>-Iſle.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A Southweſt, or Northeaſt Moon, at <hi>London, Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, Hartlepole, Whitby, Amſterdam, Gaſconygne, Galizia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. A Southweſt by weſt, or Northeaſt by eaſt Moon, at <hi>Berwick, Flamboroughhead, Burlington-bay, Oſtend, Fluſhing Burdeaux, Fountneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. When the Moon is W. S. W, or E. N. E. it's full Sea at <hi>Scarburgh,</hi> quarter tide, <hi>Lawrens, Mountis</hi>-bay <hi>Seaverin, Kingſail, Cork, Haven, Baltamore, Dungarrin, Callis, Creek, Blay,</hi> ſeven <hi>Iſles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. A W. by S. or E. by N. Moon, at <hi>Falmouth, Foy, Humber, Merles, Newcaſtle, Dartmouth, Forby, Coldby, Gernſey,</hi> St. <hi>Mallowes, Arbroth, Liſard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. An E. or W. Moon makes full ſea at <hi>Plymouth, Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth, Hull, Lin, Lundy, Antwerp, Holines</hi> of <hi>Briſtol, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids head, Concalo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. An E. by S. or W. by N. Moon at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and at <hi>Foulneſſe</hi> at the <hi>Start.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. An E. S. E. or W. N. W. Moon at <hi>Milford, Bridge Water, Ex-water, Lands-end, Waterford, Cupcleer, Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warick, Texel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. A S. E. by W. or N. W. by W. Moon, at <hi>Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Peterport, Harflew, Hague,</hi> St. <hi>Magnes ſound, Dublin, Lambay, Macknels</hi> Caſtle.</p>
               <p n="13">13. A S. E. or N. W. Moon, at <hi>Pool,</hi> St. <hi>Helens, Iſle of Man, Catneſſe, Orkney, Fair Iſles, Dumbar, Kildren,</hi> the <hi>Baſſe Iſle,</hi> the <hi>Caſquers deep</hi> half tide.</p>
               <p n="14">14. A S. W. by S. or N. W. by N. Moon, at <hi>Needles, Exford, Layſto,</hi> South and North <hi>Foreland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. A S.S.E. or N. N. W. Moon, at <hi>Yarmouth, Dover, Harwich, Firth, Bullein,</hi> St. <hi>Johns deluce, Calis Road.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. A S. by E. or N. by W. Moon, at <hi>Rye, Winchley, Gorend, Thames Roads.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:66102:48"/>
               <p>I have here added a peculiar tide Table for the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Cities of <hi>Aberdeen</hi> and <hi>Dundee,</hi> the Town of <hi>Lieth</hi> and <hi>Dumbar.</hi> For which places, you have no more ado, but enter the Table with the Age of the Moon, and againſt the reſpective places, you may know for ever, when it will be full ſea in any of them, as by one example I ſhall demonſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2">Moons Age</cell>
                        <cell role="label">increaſ.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">days</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">decreſ.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">days</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2" cols="2">Aberdeen.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H.</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">M.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>57</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2" cols="2">Dundie and S. Andrews.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">M.</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>51</cell>
                        <cell>39</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2" cols="2">Leith.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H.</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">M.</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>44</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label" rows="2" cols="2">Dumbar</cell>
                        <cell role="label">H.</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">M.</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>I demand the time of full ſea at <hi>Leith</hi> the 20 day of <hi>February,</hi> 1662. the ſaid day the Moons Age is 12. With which I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Table, and finding 12 the Moons Age on the top of the Table, I deſcend the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn, until I come againſt <hi>Leith,</hi> and I find a 11. 8. <hi>viz.</hi> a 11 h. 8 m. in the forenoon it's full ſea at <hi>Leith</hi> the 20 of <hi>February</hi> 1662. as was required. In like manner, the Moon being 12 days old, it will be full ſea at <hi>Aberdeen</hi> at 10 h. at 11 m. paſt. At <hi>Dundie</hi> or St. <hi>Andrews</hi> at 11 h. 51 m. and at <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar</hi> at 6 h. 36 min.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:49"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>REader, An urgent buſineſſe into the Weſt, occaſioned my Remotion from the Preſſe, which did exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Impede my neceſſary Attendance thereon. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, at my Return, I diligently examined the Printed Sheets, and I cannot but highly commend the Diligence and Circumſpection of the Printers: who (not being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this kind of Learning (and which is more) not having my Attendance for Correction of the Erratas, yet) have ſufficiently acquitted themſelves. However, if thou, in thy peruſal, meet with any faults; whither Literal, Sylabical, Dictional or Sententional (for it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, conſidering the Premiſes, to evade ſome, or all of theſe, eſpecially in a work of this nature, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt thy courteſie to amend it with thy Pen, omitting all cenſorious Imputations.</p>
            <p>In the ſeveral Propoſitions of <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> I confeſſe, I ſhould have been ſomewhat more plain, in giving you the practical operations by the Sines and Tangents, as I did there ſeveral Analogy's: But preſuppoſing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious to underſtand the latter, he cannot but (with ſmall pains) overcome the former. Beſides, it would have exceeded my limits in this place, to have illuſtrated the whole Propoſitions in <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> by Precept and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; but I ſhould not have been ſo brief, could I poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly have procured more time, which by no means would be granted: And therefore I reſerve theſe untill a more convenient opportunity. — Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die veneris,</hi> 18 <hi>Apr.</hi> 4 h. 30 m. A. M. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>Soli DEO Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:49"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS. CHAPTER I.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF</hi> the Names and Natures of the Signs, Planets and Aſpects. <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Of ſeveral Terms of Art, neceſſary for all Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to underſtand. <hi>p. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Of the Syſtemn of the World, and Motion of the Earth. <hi>p. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Of the Eclipſes of the Sun and Moon. <hi>p. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> To find how long the Effects of an Eclipſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues, and when they begin and end. <hi>p. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap, 6.</hi> The Names of the Regions, Cities and Towns, ſubject to the Signs and Planets. <hi>p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> To Prognoſticate the Naturall Portents of Eclipſes. <hi>p. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> To find the Lords of the Year, and four Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereof. <hi>p. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Of the ſignification of the twelve Coeleſtial Houſes. <hi>p. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Of the Diſtances, Magnitudes and Colours of the ſeven Planets. <hi>p. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Of the Trees, Herbs, and Plants, under the government of the ſeven Planets. <hi>p. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Of the particular Diſeaſes which the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets ſignifie. <hi>p. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Shewing how to rectifie a Nativity by the trutine of Herms. <hi>p. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Of the Year what it is, and the quantity thereof. <hi>p. 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Of the Judgement of the Weather from the Coeleſtial Bodies. <hi>p. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> How to Prognoſticate more particularly of the Weather by the Planets mutual Aſpects. <hi>p. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> Vulgar Obſervations of the changes of the Weather. <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:66102:50"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> Of the Winds, their Names and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>p. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 19.</hi> How to Prognoſticate what Winds will blow. <hi>p. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 20.</hi> Of Earthquakes, Thunders, Lightnings, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their natural cauſes and ſignifications. <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 21.</hi> Containing ſeverall Propoſitions in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy. <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 22.</hi> To find the true time of the Suns riſing and ſetting, with the length of the day and night for any day of the Month aſſign'd. <hi>p. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 23.</hi> To find the <hi>Golden Numbers, Epacts,</hi> and age of the Moon for any year of God aſſign'd. <hi>p. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 24.</hi> To find the time of the Moons riſing and ſetting, and how long She ſhines. <hi>p. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 25.</hi> To find the Dominical Letters, and dayes of the Week that begins every Month, and Moveable Feaſts for ever. <hi>p. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 26.</hi> Of the deſcription of the <hi>Quadrant,</hi> and how to find the Altitude of the Sun, Moon or Stars thereby. <hi>p. 65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 27.</hi> How to find the Altitude of any Tower, Caſtle or Steeple, <hi>&amp;c. p. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 28.</hi> How to find out the Latitude of a place, or the Poles Elevation above the Horizon. <hi>p 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 29.</hi> So find the Diameter, Circumference, Solidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Superficies of any Sphere or Globe. <hi>p. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 30.</hi> How to find the weight of a Globe or Ball of Mettall or Stone, without weighing them in Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances. <hi>p. 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 31.</hi> Of the Planets <hi>Paralaxis Altitudinis,</hi> and how to calculate the ſame at all times. <hi>p. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 32.</hi> To find the Lord of the hour for any tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aſſign'd. <hi>p. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 33.</hi> Shewing what Moon makes full ſea, in moſt Sea-Port Towns, in <hi>Scotland, England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland. p. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66102:50"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
